<?xml version='1.0' encoding='iso-8859-1'?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY llversion '3.0.62'>]>

  <book id="docbook">

  <bookinfo>


<!--

    this is lifelines.xml

    To use this file with SGML software, replace the text above
    this comments section with the following:

_________________________________________________________

<!DOCTYPE BOOK PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V3.1//EN" [
	<!entity llversion	"3.0.62">
]>	
	
<book id="docbook">
  <?dbhtml filename="ll-doc.htm">
  <bookinfo>
_________________________________________________________


    Rafal Prinke <rafalp@amu.edu.pl> 1-Apr-200
    - Converted original LifeLines Reference Guide to DocBook SGML.


    Marc Nozell <marc@nozell.com>  26-Jul-2001
    - Changed <simpara> to <para>.  Newer docbook likes it better.

    Marc Nozell <marc@nozell.com>  21-Sep-2000
    - updated license info
    - point to lifelines.sourceforge.net
    - change references from lines302 to llines
    - make most lines less than 80 characters wide

    Rafal Prinke <rafalp@amu.edu.pl> 30-Dec-2001
    - Converted to XML.
          - closed all <para> elements
          - defined and corrected llversion entity
          - closed empty tag <void />
          - converted all tags to lower case
          - replaced ampersands with entities
          - added space at end of line
          - parsed against DocBook 4.1.2 DTD

                                                       -->
<!-- ================================================= -->

    <title>

<application>LifeLines</application> Documentation
</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
     <firstname>Thomas T. </firstname>
     <surname>Wetmore </surname>
     <lineage>IV</lineage>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <subtitle><application>LifeLines</application> Version &llversion;</subtitle>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>

    <title>

Users' Manual

</title>

    <sect1>


      <title>

INTRODUCTION

</title>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> is a genealogy program
     that runs on <acronym>UNIX</acronym> systems. It maintains
     genealogical records (persons, families, sources, events and
     others) in a database, and generates reports from those
     records. There are no practical limits on the number of
     records that can be stored in a
     <application>LifeLines</application> database, nor on the
     amounts or kinds of data that can be kept in the
     records. <application>LifeLines</application> does not contain
     built-in reports.  Instead it provides a programming subsystem
     that you use to program your own reports and charts. The
     programming subsystem also lets you query your databases and
     process your data in any
     way. <application>LifeLines</application> uses the terminal
     independent features of <acronym>UNIX</acronym> to provide a
     screen and menu based user interface.

</para>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> is a non-commercial,
     experimental system that is use at your own risk software. I
     developed <application>LifeLines</application> for personal
     use and shared it with friends. Enough of a demand arose
     through word of mouth and internet, that I have made the
     <application>LifeLines</application> source code and other
     information freely available under an MIT-style license
     reproduced below:

</para>

<para>
     <quote>
Copyright (c) 1991-1999 Thomas T. Wetmore IV

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining
a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the
"Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction, including
without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish,
distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to
permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to
the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE
LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION
OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION
WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.

     </quote>

</para>

<para>

     The source code, documentation and a collection of report
     scripts are located at <ulink url="http://lifelines.sourceforge.net/">
     http://lifelines.sourceforge.net/</ulink>.  You can also find
     binary kits for some platforms.  If you are a developer and
     wish to contribute enhancements, please sign up on sourceforge
     and contact <ulink url="mailto:marc@nozell.com"> Marc
     Nozell</ulink> who is currently managing the project.
     </para>

     <note>
     <para>
     Prior to 1999, Lifelines was available on the ftp sites,
     <ulink url="ftp://ftp.cac.psu.edu">ftp.cac.psu.edu</ulink> and
     <ulink url="ftp://hoth.stsci.edu">hoth.stsci.edu</ulink>.
     Please use sourceforge instead.
     </para>
     </note>

<para>
Other sources of information include:

<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='none'>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>lifelines homepage
</entry><entry>
<ulink url="http://lifelines.sourceforge.net/">
http://lifelines.sourceforge.net/</ulink>.
</entry>
</row><row>
<entry>lifelines FAQ
</entry><entry>
<ulink url="http://lifelines.sourceforge.net/faq.html">
http://lifelines.sourceforge.net/faq.html</ulink>.
</entry>
</row><row>
<entry>LINES-L mailing list
</entry><entry>
<ulink url="http://listserv.nodak.edu/cgi-bin/wa.exe?A0=lines-l">
http://listserv.nodak.edu/cgi-bin/wa.exe?A0=lines-l</ulink>.
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

</para>


</sect1>



<sect1>

<title>
INSTALLATION
</title>

<para>
You may be installing <application>LifeLines</application>
from a source distribution package or as an executable program
already prepared for your <acronym>UNIX</acronym>
(or <acronym>MS-Windows</acronym>) system. The
source distribution comes with the readme, build script and
make files necessary to build
<application>LifeLines</application>. Follow the instructions
in the readme file.  A number of executables are built
which can be put it in a
directory in your execution path. If you get the program in
executable form, follow whatever instructions came with it.
The following executables are included:
</para>
<glosslist>

<glossentry><glossterm><command>btedit</command></glossterm><glossdef>
<para>
a low-level editor for advanced debugging of broken <application>LifeLines</application> databases.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><command>dbverify</command></glossterm><glossdef>
<para>
a utility program to verify <application>LifeLines</application> databases.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><command>llexec</command></glossterm><glossdef>
<para>
a stripped down version of the
<application>LifeLines</application> program, without the user interface
for non-interactive processing of report programs
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><command>llines</command></glossterm><glossdef>
<para>
the <application>LifeLines</application> program with full user interface
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>


</glosslist>

<para>
The source distribution package also contains documentation
and some <application>LifeLines</application> programs to demonstrate
the capabilities of the report language.
Included with these in the reports directory is a brief overview
of the reports in the file index.html.
</para>


</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

STARTING <application>LIFELINES</application> AND CREATING DATABASES

</title>



<para>

     You normally start <application>LifeLines</application> with
     the command: <userinput><command>llines</command> <replaceable class="parameter">database</replaceable></userinput> where
     database is the name of a <application>LifeLines</application>
     database. If <application>LifeLines</application> finds the
     database, <application>LifeLines</application> opens the
     database and takes you to the program's main menu. If the
     database doesn't exist, <application>LifeLines</application>
     asks whether it should create it, and if you answer yes, does
     so. You may create any number of databases, but only one can
     be accessed by <application>LifeLines</application> at a
     time. 

</para>



<para>

     The full command line interface to
     <application>LifeLines</application> is:

     <synopsis>
        <command>llines</command> <option>[-acdfiklnortuwxzCFI]</option><replaceable class="parameter">[database]</replaceable>
     </synopsis>

</para>



<para>

     The following options are supported:

</para>

<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='none'>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<colspec colwidth='0.5in'></colspec>
<tbody>

<row>
<entry>-C</entry>
<entry>Specify configuration file location (e.g.
-C/home/bill/lifelines/.linesrc2 ) see the section on System and User Properties below</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-F</entry>
<entry>Finnish option (only available if so compiled)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-I</entry>
<entry>
Specify a user property (e.g. -ILLEDITOR=gvim)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-a</entry>
<entry>log dynamic memory operation (for debugging)</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-c</entry>
<entry>supply cache values (eg, -ci400,4000f400,4000 sets direct indi &amp; fam
caches to 400, and indirect indi &amp; fam caches to 4000)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-d</entry>
<entry>
debug mode (signal protection disabled for convenience with breakpoints)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-f</entry>
<entry>
force open the database - use only in emergency
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-i</entry>
<entry>
open database with immutable access (no protection against other
access -- for use on read-only media)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-k</entry>
<entry>
always show keys (normally keys are suppressed if REFN available)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-l</entry>
<entry>
lock (-ly) or unlock (-ln) a database for use with read only media
(access to a locked database is treated as immutable)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-n</entry>
<entry>
do not use traditional family rules
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-o</entry>
<entry>
Specify program output filename (eg, -o/tmp/mytests)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-r</entry>
<entry>
open database with read-only access (protect against other
writer access)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-t</entry>
<entry>
trace function calls in report programs (for debugging)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-u</entry>
<entry>
specify window size (eg, -u120,34 specifies 120 columns by 34 rows)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-w</entry>
<entry>
open database with writeable access (protect against other
writer or reader access)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-x</entry>
<entry>
execute a single lifelines report program directly
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>-z</entry>
<entry>
Use normal ASCII characters for drawing lines in user interface rather
than the vt100 special characters.
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para>
the <option>-o</option> option specifies the initial filename to use for
output when running reports.  It only applies to reports run with the 
<option>-x</option> option.  This option has no effect on interactively run
programs.
</para>

<para>

     The <option>-r</option> option opens the database with read-only
     access. When in this mode
     <application>LifeLines</application> will not let you modify
     the database; no other operations are affected. The
     <option>-w</option> option opens the database with writeable
     access. If the database cannot be opened with the requested
     mode <application>LifeLines</application> quits
     immediately. When you open a database with neither the
     <option>-r</option> or <option>-w</option> options,
     <application>LifeLines</application> first tries to open the
     database with writeable access; if not possible
     <application>LifeLines</application> then tries to open the
     database with read-only access; and if this is not possible
     <application>LifeLines</application> quits. A
     <application>LifeLines</application> database may be open
     simultaneously by any number of programs with read-only
     access; however, if a database is open by a program with
     writeable access, then it cannot be opened by any other other
     program.

</para>



<para>

     In rare situations the read/write mode mechanism can fail;
     when this happens a database may appear unopenable. If this
     happens use the <option>-f</option> option to force open the
     database; this will open the database and reset the mode
     mechanism. This is a dangerous feature; you can use it to open
     the same database with writeable access more than once; the
     results are unpredictable and generally disastrous.

</para>

<para>

     The multiuser protection supplied by this reader/writer access
     mechanism is provided via a flag setting in the database, so both
     read-only and writeable access actually alter the database (read-only
     access only alters the value of this flag). For truly read-only
     access, e.g., for use with read-only media, the best solution is to
     lock (-ly) the      database before copying it to the read-only media. This
     annotates the database itself as being for immutable access.
     Alternatively, to use a database already on read-only media and not
     so annotated, use the immutable (-i) flag.

</para>

<para>
By default lifelines supports a traditional family concept, that is, each
family has at most one father and one mother.  The -n flag relaxes this
restriction.  However, not all the code in lifelines supports these
relaxations.  For example, the default family browse screen will only display
two parents, however by switching to one of the gedcom modes of displaying the
family you can see all the data.
</para>

<para>

     If you don't give the name of a database on the command line,
     <application>LifeLines</application> will prompt you for
     it.  If the name you supply is an absolute pathname or a
     relative pathname it is used as the path to the database.
     If you provided a simple filename and you use the
     <envar>LLDATABASES</envar> variable or user options (described later),
     <application>LifeLines</application> will search for the
     database in the directories named in the variable; this can be
     very convenient.
     If <envar>LLDATABASES</envar> is not set
     the filename you enter is looked for in the current working directory.

</para>

<para>

     If you would like to choose a database from a list of existing ones,
     enter a single question mark and press return when
     <application>LifeLines</application> prompts you for the database name.
     <application>LifeLines</application> will then display a list of all
     databases that it can find, and you may select one from the list.

</para>


</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

INTRODUCTION TO <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym>

</title>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> records are stored in
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> format; you organize, edit and
     maintain your data in this format. <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym>
     is a standard that defines a file format for moving
     genealogical data between computer
     systems. <application>LifeLines</application> has adopted this
     format for structuring the records in its databases. This
     approach provides a structured yet flexible method for storing
     all the data you wish to record. There are few restrictions on
     the format, amount or type of information you may store in a
     <application>LifeLines</application> database.

</para>



<para>

     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> is defined at two levels. At the
     syntactic level <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> is a simple set of
     rules for organizing and structuring data into records, with
     no concern about the types of records, types or formats of
     information in the records, or the relationships between
     records. At the semantic level <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> adds
     an additional set of rules that specify what record types are
     allowed, how records must be structured, how data within the
     records must be identified and formatted, and what specific
     relationships between the record types are allowed. In
     principle there can be multiple semantic versions of
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym>, though in practice there is only
     one, lineage-linked <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym>. Unfortunately
     this semantic version of <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> is poorly
     defined, and every genealogical system has interpreted it in
     different ways.

</para>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> uses
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> primarily at the syntactic level,
     though it does impose a few of the generally accepted
     lineage-linked semantic restrictions. This means some
     important things. It means that you can store all your
     genealogical data in your <application>LifeLines</application>
     database, and that you have wide freedom in how you choose
     your own conventions for structuring and formatting your
     data. But it also means that the way you store data in your
     databases can be different from the way that someone else
     stores their data.  This can be a problem if you share data
     with others or share report programs with other
     <application>LifeLines</application> users. My recommendation
     is to use <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> lineage-linking
     conventions wherever possible.

</para>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> does not use forms or
     screens to guide you through entering or changing
     data. Instead you use a screen editor and directly edit the
     data records. This requires you to understand the
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> format, and be able to edit data in
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> format, before you can use
     <application>LifeLines</application>. The
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> format is quite simple; this
     introduction will provide all you need to know about
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> in order to use
     <application>LifeLines</application>.

</para>



<para>

     Here is an example <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> person record:

<example>

<title>

 <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> person record

</title>

<programlisting role="gedcom">
  0 @I25@ INDI
  1 NAME <userinput>Thomas Trask /Wetmore/ Sr</userinput>
  1 SEX <userinput>M</userinput>
  1 BIRT
    2 DATE <userinput>13 March 1866</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>St. Mary's Bay, Digby, Nova Scotia</userinput>
    2 SOUR <userinput>Social Security application</userinput>
  1 NATU
    2 NAME <userinput>Thomas T. Wetmore</userinput>
    2 DATE <userinput>26 October 1888</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>Norwich, New London, Connecticut</userinput>
    2 AGE <userinput>22 years</userinput>
    2 COUR <userinput>New London County Court of Common Pleas</userinput>
    2 SOUR <userinput>court record from National Archives</userinput>
  1 OCCU <userinput>Antiques Dealer</userinput>
  1 DEAT
    2 NAME <userinput>Thomas Trask Wetmore</userinput>
    2 DATE <userinput>17 February 1947</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>New London, New London, Connecticut</userinput>
    2 AGE <userinput>80 years, 11 months, 4 days</userinput>
    2 CAUS <userinput>Heart Attack</userinput>
    2 SOUR <userinput>New London Death Records</userinput>
  1 FAMC @F11@
  1 FAMS @F6@
  1 FAMS @F12@

</programlisting></example>

</para>



<para>

     A <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> record is made up of lines. Each
     line has a level number and a tag, and most lines have a value
     following the tag. The first line in every record has a
     cross-reference index between the level number and the tag.

</para>



<para>

     Level numbers allow data to be structured to any degree of
     detail; lines with higher level numbers expand on lines with
     lower numbers. Each record begins at level 0, and each deeper
     level increments the level by
     one. <application>LifeLines</application> does not restrict
     the structuring depth. Tags are uppercase (by convention) code
     words that specify the kind of information on the line or on
     the higher numbered lines that follow. The information after
     the tag, if any, is the value of the line.

</para>



<para>

     The first line in a record indicates its type. There are four
     fixed record types in <application>LifeLines</application>
     databases: person, family, source and event. The first, 0
     level line in these records have tags
     <structname>INDI</structname>, <structname>FAM</structname>,
     <structname>SOUR</structname> and
     <structname>EVEN</structname>, respectively. Besides these
     record types, you may create your own record types by using
     any other tag on the 0 level line of a record. The lines that
     begin records are the only level 0 lines used in
     <application>LifeLines</application>. Each level 0 line has a
     cross-reference index between the level number and the
     tag. This index is the record's internal reference key; other
     records may refer to this record by using this index.
     Cross-reference indexes are bracketed by @ characters.

</para>



<para>

     The first line in the example record has the
     <structname>INDI</structname> tag, identifying it as a
     person. The cross-reference index value, I25, can be used by
     other records to refer to this record.

</para>



<para>

     The second line in the example has the person's name. Each
     person record in a <application>LifeLines</application>
     database must have at least one <structfield>1
     NAME</structfield> line, and its value must be in
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> name format. This format allows
     names to be as long as needed, but the surname, which may be
     placed anywhere in the name, must be separated from the rest
     of the name by one or two slashes. For example:

<example>

<title>
Example of NAME formats

</title>

<programlisting>
1 NAME <userinput>John/Smith</userinput>
1 NAME <userinput>John /Smith/</userinput>
1 NAME <userinput>John/Smith/Jr.</userinput>
</programlisting>
</example>

</para>



<para>

     The second slash is required only if name elements follow the
     surname. White space is optional before the first slash and
     after the second. If you don't know a person's surname, or the
     person doesn't have a surname, you may use / or // or no
     slashes at all. For example:

<example>

<title>
Example of searching on NAMEs
</title>

<programlisting>

1 NAME <userinput>Mary//</userinput>
1 NAME <userinput>Mary/</userinput>
1 NAME <userinput>Mary</userinput>
</programlisting>

</example>

     are all ways to enter a person named Mary with no known
     surname. A person may have any number, including zero, given
     names and/or initials. A <application>LifeLines</application>
     person record may have any number of <structfield>1
     NAME</structfield> lines, though the person will be displayed
     with the first name value only. Persons are indexed under all
     their names, however, so you will be able to search for
     persons by any of their names.
</para>



<para>

     The next line in the example gives the person's
     sex. <application>LifeLines</application> doesn't require a
     <structfield>1 SEX</structfield> line, but you should include
     it. The value of the line should be <userinput>M</userinput>
     or <userinput>F</userinput> if the sex is known; it can be
     left blank or set to <userinput>U</userinput> or
     <userinput>?</userinput>, say, if not known. A person must
     have a <structfield>1 SEX</structfield> line with a value of
     either <userinput>M</userinput> or <userinput>F</userinput>
     before he or she can be made a spouse or parent in a family.

</para>



<para>

     The example record also contains three events: birth,
     naturalization, and death. An event begins with a level 1 line
     whose tag indicates the event type. For example,
     <structfield>BIRT</structfield> is the tag for a birth event.

</para>



<para>

     Events usually have at least a <structfield>2
     DATE</structfield> and a <structfield>2 PLAC</structfield>
     line and often a <structfield>2 SOUR</structfield> line. The
     <structfield>DATE</structfield> and
     <structfield>PLAC</structfield> lines give the date and place
     of the event. The value of a
     <application>LifeLines</application>
     <structfield>DATE</structfield> line is free format, though
     <application>LifeLines</application> will try to parse it for
     specific day, month and year information. The value of a
     <structfield>PLAC</structfield> line is usually a
     comma-separated list of geopolitical units, starting with the
     most specific, ending with the most general. The
     <structfield>SOUR</structfield> line indicates the source of
     information about the event. The
     <structfield>SOUR</structfield> line can be the root of a full
     description of the source, or the value of the
     <structfield>SOUR</structfield> line can be a cross-reference
     key that refers to the source record that describes the
     source.

</para>



<para>

     The naturalization event (with tag
     <structfield>NATU</structfield>) shows a few other lines. The
     <structfield>2 NAME</structfield> line gives the person's name
     as recorded in the source (only <structfield>1
     NAME</structfield> lines must follow <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym>
     format). The <structfield>2 AGE</structfield> line gives the
     person's age at the time of the event. The <structfield>2
     COUR</structfield> line indicates the court where
     naturalization occurred.

</para>



<para>

     The final event is a death event (tag
     <structfield>DEAT</structfield>). The <structfield>2
     CAUS</structfield> line gives the cause of death.

</para>



<para>

     At the end of the record are three lines that refer to family
     records. A <structfield>1 FAMC</structfield> line refers to a
     family record that the person belongs to as a child; its value
     is the cross-reference index value of that family.  A
     <structfield>1 FAMS</structfield> line refers to a family
     record that the person belongs to as a spouse or parent.

</para>



<para>

     When using <application>LifeLines</application> to edit a
     person, you will not be able to edit the cross reference
     values on the <structfield>0 INDI</structfield>,
     <structfield>1 FAMC</structfield> or <structfield>1
     FAMS</structfield> lines; these are maintained by
     <application>LifeLines</application>.

</para>



<para>

     Here is an example family record:

<example>

<title>
Example family record
</title>

<programlisting>

  0 @F6@ FAM
  1 HUSB @I25@
  1 WIFE @I26@
  1 MARR
    2 DATE <userinput>31 March 1891</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>New London, New London, Connecticut</userinput>
    2 SOUR <userinput>New London Vital Records</userinput>
  1 CHIL @I27@
  1 CHIL @I17@</programlisting></example>

</para>



<para>

     The <structfield>0 FAM</structfield> line assigns the family
     the cross-reference index of F6. The record contains
     <structfield>1 HUSB</structfield> and <structfield>1
     WIFE</structfield> lines that refer to the two
     spouses/parents. The record also holds a marriage event (tag
     <structfield>MARR</structfield>) and two <structfield>1
     CHIL</structfield> lines that refer to two children in the
     family. When editing family records, you cannot edit the
     <structfield>0 FAM</structfield>, <structfield>1
     HUSB</structfield>, <structfield>1 WIFE</structfield>, or
     <structfield>1 CHIL</structfield> lines; these are maintained
     by <application>LifeLines</application>.

</para>

<para>

     When you create new records for your database, you are free to
     invent tags and structure your data in any way you see
     fit. However, it is good practice to use standard
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> tags and value formats.
     <application>LifeLines</application> does enforce a small set
     of conventions that you must obey. Within person records,
     <application>LifeLines</application> requires that you use
     <structfield>1 NAME</structfield> and <structfield>1
     SEX</structfield> lines with their special meanings and value
     formats. Though not required,
     <application>LifeLines</application> assumes that you will use
     <structfield>1 BIRT</structfield>, <structfield>1
     DEAT</structfield>, <structfield>1 CHR</structfield>, and
     <structfield>1 BURI</structfield> lines for birth, death,
     baptism and burial events, respectively. In family records,
     <application>LifeLines</application> assumes you will use the
     <structfield>1 MARR</structfield> event for marriage
     events. Within person records, you are not allowed to use
     <structfield>0 INDI</structfield>, <structfield>1
     FAMC</structfield> or <structfield>1 FAMS</structfield> lines,
     since these are used to maintain linkage information. Within
     family records, you are not allowed to use <structfield>0
     FAM</structfield>, <structfield>1 HUSB</structfield>,
     <structfield>1 WIFE</structfield> or <structfield>1
     CHIL</structfield> lines.

</para>



<para>

     The indentation shown in the examples is not part of
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> format. When
     <application>LifeLines</application> prepares records for you
     to edit, however, it always indents the records, making them
     easier to read and understand. You do not need to follow this
     indentation scheme when you edit the records. Indentation is
     removed from the data before it is stored in the database.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

MAIN MENU

</title>



<para>

     After <application>LifeLines</application> opens an existing
     database, or creates a new one, it presents you with the main
     menu:

<screen>
Please choose an operation:
   b Browse the persons in the database
   s Search database
   a Add information to the database
   d Delete information from the database
   p Pick a report from list and run
   r Generate report by entering report name
   t Modify character translation tables
   u Miscellaneous utilities
   x Handle source, event and other records
   Q Quit current database
   q Quit program
</screen>


</para>

<para>

     Select an operation by striking the proper selection letter.

</para>



<para>

     The browse operation lets you browse the database and perform
     many operations on the data. The search operation provides some
     simple wildcard search capabilities, which lead into browsing
     particular records. The add operation lets you add
     new information, and the delete operation removes
     information. The report operations read report
     programs and generates output reports. The modify character
     translation tables operation changes the translation
     tables. The miscellaneous utilities operation provides such
     things as backup and restore. The handle source, event and
     other records operation gives you access to these three record
     types. The quit operation closes the database and returns to
     <acronym>UNIX</acronym>.

</para>



<para>

     The browse operation deserves special mention, because it
     provides a rich environment for searching, viewing, adding,
     modifying, merging and deleting information in the
     database. You will find that you operate from the browsing
     modes most of the time. The operations are all described in
     later sections.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

CODESET

</title>

<para>

     After you have created a new database, and before you actually
     add any data to it, is the time to set the codeset to be used
     in the database.

</para>

<para>

     The codeset (or character encoding, to use precise Unicode
     terminology) is the decision as to how letters will be represented
     by the computer. If you have only ever used English letters in
     computing, you may not have had to encounter this issue, because as
     it happens, the English letters (a-z and A-Z) are stored numerically
     in the same fashion in almost all codesets used by computers. However,
     in the field of genealogy, you are especially likely to meet letters
     outside of the English alphabet (for example, accented vowels).

</para>

<para>

     You have fundamentally three choices as to what codeset to use in your
     database, listed below from easiest to most powerful.

</para>

<para>

     First, you may leave it entirely unspecified. This will give the 
     traditional lifelines behavior. This is really only suitable if either
     (a), you only use English (ASCII) data, or (b), you work in an 
     environment which entirely uses the same 8-bit codeset (eg, a GNU/Linux box
     which is all ISO-8859-15), and you only run lifelines in English.
     If you use any non-English data on MS-Windows, this is not likely to 
     be suitable, because the lifelines screens run in the console, but 
     you are likely to use MS-Windows applications either for editing or 
     for viewing output, and the MS-Windows console uses a different 
     codeset from MS-Windows applications. Also, if you use lifelines in a
     different language than English, this may not be suitable, because 
     the gettext message catalogs (for non-English interface) will not 
     be converted into your codeset.

</para>

<para>

     Second, you may specify a particular 8-bit codeset. Assuming that you
     have iconv and gettext installed (or you are using the MS-Windows version,
     which comes with these), you may specify any 8-bit codeset supported by
     iconv, and iconv supports quite many. A natural choice for Western European
     languages would be ISO-8859-1, or (for MS-Windows only) CP-1252. With this
     option, gettext language files will be converted to your codeset.

</para>

<para>

     Third, you may specify the use of UTF-8. This is a Unicode encoding, and
     is by far the most powerful option. In fact, this is the only really
     convenient way to be able to store, for example, names in English, names
     in Russian, and names in Greek, all in the same database, in their native
     scripts (alphabets).  In recent versions, lifelines has become more
     knowledgeable about handling UTF-8, so that, for example, upper &amp;
     lower casing only work correctly with versions from 3.0.28 on.

</para>

<para>

     To actually specify a codeset, enter it via the u(tility) o(ptions) page
     (which is documented below). From the main menu, in the English version,
     press u to reach the utility page, and then o to edit the user options. To
     set a codeset of, e.g., ISO-8859-1, enter this string on its own line,
     without the surrounding quotes: "codeset=ISO-8859-1". Or, to specify the
     use of UTF-8, "codeset=UTF-8".

</para>

<para>

     Further information about codeset conversion is found in the later chapter
     of that name (for example, information about producing reports which make
     use of HTML entity names for non-ASCII characters).

</para>

</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

ENTERING THE FIRST PERSON

</title>

<para>

     Note: Before you add the first person to your database, you
     specify internal codeset (review the Codeset chapter for
     information).

</para>

<para>

     Normally you add persons to the database from the browsing
     modes, but when entering the first person there is no one in
     the database to browse to. To add the first person to a
     <application>LifeLines</application> database, first select
     the add operation from the main menu. You will be prompted
     with the add menu (described later).  Strike p to add a
     person. <application>LifeLines</application> creates a
     template of a <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> person record, and
     puts you in a screen editor to edit the template. The default
     template is:

<example>
<title>
Default person record template
</title>

<programlisting>

  0 INDI
  1 NAME <replaceable>Fname /Surname/</replaceable>
  1 SEX <replaceable>MF</replaceable>
  1 BIRT
    2 DATE
    2 PLAC
    2 SOUR
  1 DEAT
    2 DATE
    2 PLAC
    2 SOUR</programlisting></example>

</para>



<para>

     Edit the template to create the new person's record. Change
     the name to the person's name. Assign the person's sex by
     deleting either <userinput>M</userinput> or
     <userinput>F</userinput>. Fill out the birth and death events
     as best you can. If the person is alive, remove the death
     event. Remove any <structfield>DATE</structfield> and
     <structfield>PLAC</structfield> lines you do not have the
     information for.

</para>



<para>

     The default template provides lines for one birth and one
     death event. You can expand the record with other events (even
     more birth or death events) and lines. Indentation makes it
     easier to read and edit the record, but isn't necessary. You
     may change the default edit template by defining the user
     option <option>INDIREC</option> (described later).

</para>



<para>

     Here is how I might edit the template when creating a record
     about myself:

<example>

<title>
Example editing of template record
</title>

<programlisting>

  0 INDI
  1 NAME <userinput>Thomas Trask /Wetmore/ IV</userinput>
  1 SEX <userinput>M</userinput>
  1 BIRT
    2 DATE <userinput>18 December 1949</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>New London, New London, Connecticut</userinput>
    2 SOUR <userinput>Birth Certificate</userinput>
  1 OCCU <userinput>Software Engineer</userinput>
  1 RESI
    2 DATE <userinput>1982 to 1995</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>Newburyport, Essex, Massachusetts</userinput>
    2 ADDR <userinput>2 Barton Street, Newburyport, MA 01950</userinput>

... lots of other events and facts
</programlisting>
</example>

</para>



<para>

     When you edit a person record, don't add or modify
     <structfield>INDI</structfield>,
     <structfield>FAMC</structfield> or
     <structfield>FAMS</structfield>
     lines. <application>LifeLines</application> creates and
     maintains these lines through specific user commands.

</para>



<para>

     When you finish editing and leave the editor, you
     automatically return to
     <application>LifeLines</application>. If you made an error
     (eg, didn't use proper level numbers or didn't follow the
     proper name convention), <application>LifeLines</application>
     displays an error message, and asks if you want to re-edit the
     record. If you don't, <application>LifeLines</application>
     doesn't add the person to the database.

</para>



<para>

     When the record is in proper format,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks if you are sure you
     want to add the person to the database. If you answer yes, the
     person is added; if you answer no, the person isn't. In both
     cases <application>LifeLines</application> returns to the main
     menu.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

SCREEN EDITORS AND ENVIRONMENT VARIABLES

</title>



<para>

     With <application>LifeLines</application> you maintain the
     database records using a screen editor. This is different than
     other genealogical programs where screens or forms are used to
     gather the data.The default screen editor for
     <application>LifeLines</application> is
     <application>vi</application>. (The <acronym>MS-Windows</acronym>
     version defaults instead to notepad.exe.) This can be overridden by the
     <envar>ED</envar>, <envar>EDITOR</envar> or
     <envar>LLEDITOR</envar> environment variables. For example, if
     you prefer the emacs screen editor, and if you use a bourne-compatible
     shell, you may add the line:
     <userinput><envar>ED</envar>=<replaceable>emacs</replaceable></userinput>
     to your login profile file, and
     <application>LifeLines</application> will use
     <application>emacs</application> for editing.

</para>



<para>

     There are four other, <application>LifeLines</application>
     specific environment variables. They are
     <envar>LLDATABASES</envar>, <envar>LLARCHIVES</envar>,
     <envar>LLPROGRAMS</envar> and <envar>LLREPORTS</envar>.
     <envar>LLDATABASES</envar> and
     <envar>LLPROGRAMS</envar> are <acronym>UNIX</acronym> path
     list variables.  

</para>

<para>
     There is also a configuration file, and
     entries in it may be used in lieu of environment variables.
     It is ordinarily named .linesrc under <acronym>UNIX</acronym>,
     and lines.cfg under <acronym>MS-Windows</acronym>.
     A sample configuration file should have been included
     in the distribution.
</para>

<para>
     See the section on System and User properties
     for more details.
</para>

<para>

     <envar>LLDATABASES</envar> can be set to a list of directories
     that hold <application>LifeLines</application> databases. When
     you execute the <application>LifeLines</application> program,
     these directories will be searched in turn for the database
     mentioned on the command line. For example,
     <userinput><envar>LLDATABASES</envar>=<replaceable>.:/home/ttw4/LifeLines/Databases</replaceable></userinput>
     indicates that databases should be searched for in the current
     directory first, and if not found there, then searched for in:
     <filename>/home/ttw4/LifeLines/Databases</filename>

</para>



<para>

     Each <application>LifeLines</application> database is
     implemented as a directory with specific contents. The
     <envar>LLDATABASES</envar> variable should be set to a list of
     directories that contain these database directories, not to a
     list of database directories themselves.

</para>



<para>

     The environment variable <envar>LLPROGRAMS</envar> is used in
     the same way, but to specify the search path for
     <application>LifeLines</application> report generating and
     other programs (described later).

</para>



<para>

     <envar>LLARCHIVES</envar> and <envar>LLREPORTS</envar> can
     each be set to specify a single
     directory. <envar>LLARCHIVES</envar> is used to select a
     directory where all database backup files will be stored, and
     <envar>LLREPORTS</envar> is used to select a directory where
     all generated reports and program outputs will be placed.

</para>

<para>

     New databases without explicit paths will be created in the
     first directory listed in the LLDATABASES path. (This is a 
     change; versions from 3.0.6 to 3.0.31 used a now obsolete
     variable LLNEWDBDIR).

</para>

<para>

     You are not required to use these environment variables; when
     a variable is not defined,
     <application>LifeLines</application> uses the current
     directory as its default value. If you do use the variables,
     you can override their use by specifying files and directories
     as either absolute or relative paths.

</para>

<para>

     You may use the configuration file in
     lieu of environment variables. This is especially oriented towards
     users on <acronym>MS-Windows</acronym> systems, on which
     environment variables are not as common a configuration technique.

</para>


<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> uses the curses library
     for terminal independent I/O. This requires you to specify
     your terminal type with the <envar>TERM</envar> environment
     variable. (This is not relevant in the <acronym>MS-Windows</acronym>
     version.)

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

BASICS OF BROWSING

</title>



<para>

     You will use the browsing screens of
     <application>LifeLines</application> most of the time. When in
     these modes you can quickly search for or browse through the
     persons and families in the database. When you find a person
     or family you are interested in, you can then edit their
     records.

</para>



<para>
     The browsing screens also allow you to add new persons and
     families to the database, add spouses to families, add
     children to families, swap the order of spouses and children,
     merge persons and merge families, and perform other
     operations. The browsing screens also lets you remove spouses
     from families and remove children from families.
</para>

<para>
     There are six browsing screens. The person and family screens
     concentrate on a single person and family, respectively. The
     list screen allows you to browse through a list of persons. The
     two person browse screen shows two persons at once, and the
     two family browse screen shows two families at once. The
     auxiliary screen is used browsing any other type of records
     (e.g., events, sources, notes).

</para>

<para>
     Each browsing screen has multiple
     view modes. The view mode affects how the information is displayed
     on the screen, but does not affect the menu choices available at
     the bottom of the screen. Menu commands are available on each screen
     to change amongst the view modes available for that screen.
</para>

<para>
     The person screen has the most view modes. It has normal mode,
     which shows a summary of the vital records of the person. It (like
     all other screens) has GEDCOM mode, which shows the actual GEDCOM
     data of the record, and also expanded GEDCOM mode, which shows the
     actual GEDCOM data, but augments it with information on each line
     that contains a cross-reference (GEDCOM xref). It has two pedigree
     or tree modes, one showing an ancestral tree and one showing a
     descendant tree. The depth of the pedigree trees shown may be
     adjusted via menu commands.
</para>

<para>
     The two person browse screen has the same modes as the person
     screen.
</para>

<para>
     The two family browse screen and tandem family screen alike have
     normal mode (showing a summary of vitals), GEDCOM mode, and
     expanded GEDCOM mode.
</para>

<para>
     The auxiliary screen has only GEDCOM mode and expanded GEDCOM mode.
     (The list screen has no view modes at present).
</para>

</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

IDENTIFYING A PERSON OR LIST OF PERSONS TO BROWSE

</title>



<para>

     To enter the browsing modes from the main menu strike
     b. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify a
     person or list of persons to browse to:

<screen>
Please identify person or persons to browse to.
Enter name, key, refn or list:
</screen>

</para>

<para>

     Enter either a name or partial name, or an internal key value,
     or a user-defined reference key (described later) or the name
     of a previously defined list of persons (described later), and
     strike return.

</para>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> allows wide flexibility
     in how to enter names. You may enter a name in upper or lower
     case or any combination. You may leave out all but the first
     given name, and, for given names, you may leave out any
     letters except the first. You may leave vowels out of the
     surname, and after four or five consonants have been typed,
     you may leave them out too. You must separate the given names
     from the surname by a slash, and if you enter given names
     after the surname (as in Chinese names), or any modifiers
     (such as Jr, Sr, IV, etc.), they must be separated from the
     surname by another slash. Here are a few of the ways I can
     enter my name:

<example>

<title>
Example of entering a name
</title>

<literallayout>
Thomas Trask /Wetmore/ IV
thomas/wetmore/iv
t t/wetmr/i
th tr/Wetmore
t/wtmr/iv
</literallayout>
</example>

</para>



<para>

     You may browse to the list of all persons with the same
     surname by using the * character as the first initial. For
     example:

<example>

<title>
Example of using wildcard in browsing
</title>

     <literallayout>*/wetmore</literallayout></example>matches all
     persons with surname Wetmore. This is the only wildcard
     feature supported in browsing. (However, the search operation
     provides some simple wildcards for
     finding individual name fragments, or searching by user-defined
     reference keys. The search operation is accessed via a different
     choice off of the main menu.)

</para>



<para>

     After you enter a name, <application>LifeLines</application>
     searches for all persons who match. There are three
     possibilities: no one matches; one person matches; or more
     than one person matches. In the first case
     <application>LifeLines</application> writes: 
     <screen>There is no one in the database with that name or key.</screen>
     and leaves you in the main menu.

</para>



<para>

     If one person matches, <application>LifeLines</application>
     enters the person browse mode displaying the matched
     person. If more than one person matches,
     <application>LifeLines</application> enters the list browsing
     mode with the list of matching persons.

</para>



<para>

     You may also identify a person by entering his or her
     internal, cross-reference key value. The internal key values
     of all person records are an I followed by digits.
     When you enter a key value you may omit the I.
     If <application>LifeLines</application> finds a person with
     the key value you provide,
     <application>LifeLines</application> enters the person
     browsing mode displaying that person.  You can also browse to
     a Family, Source, or Note by entering its key, but you must
     include the letter identifing the key type, thus F11, S1, or N3
     would browse to the family, source or note corresponding to the key
     if it exists.

</para>
    
<para>

     The browse command b is also available from most browsing
     modes. The command works the same way from those modes as it
     does from the main menu.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

ZIP IDENTIFYING A NEW PERSON

</title>



<para>

     Some <application>LifeLines</application> operations need you
     to identify a person, not for the purpose of browsing, but for
     the purpose of completing an operation you have requested. For
     example, when you add a child to a family,
     <application>LifeLines</application> may ask you to identify
     the child. When this happens a panel pops up that asks you to
     identify a person. You respond by typing a name or key exactly
     as you would for the b command. If no one matches,
     <application>LifeLines</application> returns to the previous
     browsing mode. If the name matches persons in the database
     <application>LifeLines</application> displays something like:

<screen>
Please choose from among these records.
  >Thomas Trask Wetmore, b. 1826, N.B. (42)
   Thomas Trask Wetmore IV, b. 1949, Conn. (1)
   Thomas Trask Wetmore III, b. 1925, Conn. (6)
   Thomas Trask Wetmore Jr, b. 1896, Conn. (11)
   Thomas Trask Wetmore Sr, b. 1866, N.S. (23)
   Thomas Trask Wetmore V, b. 1982, Mass. (5)
_______________________________________________
Commands: j Move down k Move up i Select q Quit
</screen>


</para>



<para>

     Use the j and k commands to move the selection cursor (>) to
     the correct person, and then use the i command to select that
     person. There may be more persons in the list than you can see
     at once. If this is so then you can use the j and k commands
     to scroll through the full list. If you don't find the proper
     person, use the q command and
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks whether you want to
     enter another name.

</para>

<para>

     With version 3.0.15, lists may also be navigated with the up
     and down arrows, PageUp and PageDown keys, Home and End keys, and
     the Enter key. Shift-PageUp and Shift-PageDown move more than one
     page at a time in a given direction. The keyboard equivalents are
     j=UpArrow, k=DownArrow, u=PageUp, d=PageDown, ^=Home, $=End,
     U=Shift-PageUp, D=Shift-PageDown, i=Enter.

</para>


<para>

     When <application>LifeLines</application> creates a list of
     names for you to select from, it tries to add extra
     information to the name; this helps determine which name to
     choose, and is important in databases where many persons have
     the same name. <application>LifeLines</application> also
     places the person's key value at the end of each menu line;
     this may be helpful in large databases.

</para>



<para>

     Some browse screens provide the z command, which allows you to
     browse to a new person using the zip style of identification
     rather than the b style.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

BROWSE DISPLAY BASICS

</title>



<para>

     The screen display for each browsing screen is made up of
     panels. At the bottom of each display is a message panel used
     for one line messages. Each display contains one or two data
     panels showing information from the database. And each display
     has a panel with the operation menu available for that screen.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

PERSON BROWSE SCREEN

</title>



<para>

     After you identify a person to browse to,
     <application>LifeLines</application> enters the person browse
     screen. The top panel in the display gives basic information
     about the person (in the normal, or vitals, mode, which is the
     default). The middle panel provides a menu of commands.
     For example:

<screen>
person: Thomas Trask WETMORE Sr (25)
  born: 13 March 1866, St. Mary's Bay, Digby, Nova Scotia
  died: 17 February 1947, New London, New London, Connecticut
  father: Daniel Lorenzo WETMORE, b. 1821, N.S., d. 1903, Conn. (48)
  mother: Mary Ann DOTY, b. 1824, N.S., d. 1897, Conn. (59)
  spouse: Margaret Ellen KANEEN, b. 1855, Eng., d. 1900, Conn. (26)
    child: Portia Louise WETMORE, b. 1892, Conn., d. 1921, Conn. (27)
    child: Thomas Trask WETMORE, b. 1896, Conn., d. 1970, Conn. (17)
  spouse: Arleen M KEENEY, m. 1914, Conn. (75)
_______________________________________________________________________
Please choose an operation:             (pg 1/3)
  e  Edit the person       g  Browse to family    p  Pedigree mode
  f  Browse to father      u  Browse to parents   n  Create new person
  m  Browse to mother      b  Browse to persons   a  Create new family
  s  Browse to spouse/s    h  Add as spouse       x  Swap two families
  c  Browse to children    i  Add as child        tt Enter tandem mode
  o  Browse to older sib   r  Remove as spouse    ?  Other menu choices
  y  Browse to younger sib d  Remove as child     q  Return to main menu
_______________________________________________________________________
LifeLines -- Person Browse Screen
</screen>


</para>



<para>

The commands perform a wide variety of functions.

</para>



<para>

<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit the person. </action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Edit the person's database
     record. <application>LifeLines</application> puts the record
     in a file, and then runs a screen editor so you can edit the
     record. When you return from the editor,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to confirm any
     changes; the person is changed only if you answer yes.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>f</keycap> <action>Browse to father.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the person's father. If the father isn't in the
     database, <application>LifeLines</application> doesn't change
     the display. If there are more than one father,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to select one.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap> <action>Browse to mother.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the person's mother. If the mother isn't in the
     database, <application>LifeLines</application> doesn't change
     the display. If there are more than one mother,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to select one.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>s</keycap> <action>Browse to spouse/s.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the person's spouse. If the person has more than one
     spouse, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     select one. If the person has no spouse, the display does not
     change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>c</keycap> <action>Browse to children.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to one of the person's children. If there is more than
     one child, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     select one. If the person has no children, the display does
     not change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>o</keycap> <action>Browse to older sib.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the person's next older sibling. If the person has
     no such sibling, the display does not change. Only siblings
     from the same family are browsed by this command.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>y</keycap> <action>Browse to younger sib.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the person's next younger sibling. If the person has
     no such sibling, the display does not change. Only siblings
     from the same family are browsed by this command.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>g</keycap> <action>Browse to family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the family the person is a spouse or parent in, and
     switch to the family browse mode. If the person is in more
     than one family, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you
     to identify which one. If the person is not a spouse or parent
     in any family, the display does not change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>u</keycap> <action>Browse to parents.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the family the person is a child in, and switch to
     the family browse mode. If the person is not a child in a
     family, the display does not change. If the person is a child
     in more than one family, <application>LifeLines</application>
     asks you to identify which one.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>b</keycap> <action>Browse to persons.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to a new person or list of
     persons. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify a person or persons by name, key or list name, and
     depending on how many persons are identified, switches either
     to the list browse mode, or remains in the person browse mode.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>h</keycap> <action>Add as spouse.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Add the person as a spouse/parent to an existing
     family. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the family, and then asks you to confirm the request.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>i</keycap> <action>Add as child.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Add the person as a child to an existing family. The person
     may already be a child in another
     family. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the family, and then asks you to confirm the request.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>r</keycap> <action>Remove as spouse.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Remove the person as a spouse or parent from an existing
     family. If the person is a spouse or parent in more than one
     family, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the family.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>d</keycap> <action>Remove as child.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Remove the person as a child in an existing family.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>n</keycap> <action>Create new person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Create and add a new person to the
     database. <application>LifeLines</application> creates a
     record template and puts you into the screen editor to edit
     the record. When you return from the editor,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to confirm the
     operation. If you do, the new person is added and becomes the
     current person. If not, the new person is not added, and
     <application>LifeLines</application> returns to the original
     display.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>a</keycap> <action>Create new family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Create and add a new family to the database. The new family
     may have the current person as either a spouse/parent or as a
     child; <application>LifeLines</application> asks which. If you
     choose to create a family with the person as a spouse/parent,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the
     other spouse if he or she is known. In either case
     <application>LifeLines</application> creates a family
     template, and places you in the screen editor.  When you
     return from the editor, <application>LifeLines</application>
     asks you to confirm the operation. If you do,
     <application>LifeLines</application> adds the family and
     shifts into family browse mode. If the command you ran just
     before the a command were the n command, and you choose to
     create a family with the person as a spouse/parent,
     <application>LifeLines</application> guesses that the other
     spouse in the family will be the person displayed just before
     the new person was
     created. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you if this
     is the case, and if so, automatically make that person the
     other spouse in the new family. If this is not the case,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the
     other spouse.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>p</keycap> <action>Pedigree mode.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Change to pedigree browse mode. The person becomes the root
     person in the pedigree display.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>x</keycap> <action>Swap two families.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Swap (change chronological order) any two families that the
     person belongs to as a spouse or
     parent. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the two families and then swaps them.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>tt</keycap> <action>Enter tandem mode.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Change to the tandem person browse
     mode. <application>LifeLines</application> first asks you to
     identify the second person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>?</keycap> <action>Other menu choices.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
     Go to the next page of menu choices. This will have no effect on the
     upper (data) portion of the screen, but it allows you to page through
     all available commands for this display screen.
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Return to the <application>LifeLines</application> main menu.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>z</keycap> <action>Zip browse to person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

        Zip browse to a new person.
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
        identify a person by name or key value, and if you do so,
        browses to that person.

</para>


</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</para>



</sect1>

<sect1>

<title>

LIST BROWSE SCREEN

</title>



<para>

     This browse screen handles lists of persons. The top panel shows
     information about one person in the list.  The left panel
     shows a list of up to 12 persons. The person shown in the top
     panel is identified by the > character. The right panel is the
     menu of available commands.

<screen>
person: Thomas Trask WETMORE Sr (25)
  born: 13 March 1866, St. Mary's Bay, Digby, Nova Scotia
  died: 17 February 1947, New London, New London, Connecticut
  father: Daniel Lorenzo WETMORE, b. 1821, N.S., d. 1903, Conn. (48)
  mother: Mary Ann DOTY, b. 1824, N.S., d. 1897, Conn. (59)
  spouse: Margaret Ellen KANEEN, b. 1855, Eng., d. 1900, Conn. (26)
_______________________________________________________________________
  Thomas Trask WETMORE (42)                Choose an operation:
  Thomas Trask WETMORE III (6)              j Move down list
  Thomas Trask WETMORE IV (1)               k Move up list
  Thomas Trask WETMORE (11)                 e Edit this person
 >Thomas Trask WETMORE Sr (23)              i Browse this person
  Thomas Trask WETMORE (5)                  m Mark this person
                                            r Remove from list
                                            t Enter tandem mode
                                            n Name this list
                                            b Browse new persons
                                            a Add to this list
                                            x Swap mark/current
                                            q Return to main menu
_______________________________________________________________________
LifeLines -- List Browse Screen
</screen>


</para>



<para>

<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>j</keycap> <action>Move down list.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Move down the list one person. The list panel is only large
     enough to show 12 persons. However, the list may contain many
     more persons. Use the <keycap>j</keycap> and
     <keycap>k</keycap> commands to scroll to these other persons.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>k</keycap> <action>Move up list.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Move up the list one person. The list panel is only large
     enough to show 12 persons. However, the list may contain many
     more persons. Use the <keycap>j</keycap> and
     <keycap>k</keycap> commands to scroll to these other persons.

</para>

<para>

     With version 3.0.15, lists may also be navigated with the up
     and down arrows, PageUp and PageDown keys, Home and End keys, and
     the Enter key. Shift-PageUp and Shift-PageDown move more than one
     page at a time in a given direction. The keyboard equivalents are
     j=UpArrow, k=DownArrow, u=PageUp, d=PageDown, ^=Home, $=End,
     U=Shift-PageUp, D=Shift-PageDown, i=Enter.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit this person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Edit the displayed person's database
     record. <application>LifeLines</application> runs the editor
     on the person's record. When you return from the editor,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to confirm any
     changes, and then leaves you in the list browse screen.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>i</keycap> <action>Browse this person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Change to the person browse screen with the current person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap> <action>Mark this person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Mark the current person if he/she is not marked; unmark the
     person is he/she is.  The marked person is shown with an x by
     his/her name. Marked persons are used by the t and x
     commands. Only one person may be marked at a time.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>r</keycap> <action>Remove from list.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Remove the current person from the browse list (not from the database).

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>t</keycap> <action>Enter tandem mode.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Change to the tandem person mode with the current person and
     the marked person as the two persons. If no person is marked there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>n</keycap> <action>Name this list.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Lists of persons may be named, allowing you to quickly browse
     back to them by giving a list name in response to the b
     command from different
     modes. <application>LifeLines</application> will prompt you
     for the name. List names are most convenient when short.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>b</keycap> <action>Browse new persons.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to a new person or list of persons. You can identify a
     person or list of persons by name, internal or user key or by
     list name.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>a</keycap> <action>Add to this list.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Add more persons to the current browse
     list. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify a new person or list of persons by name, key or list
     name, and they are added to and name-sorted into the current
     list.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>x</keycap> <action>Swap mark/current.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Swap the current person with the marked person in the list.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Return to the <application>LifeLines</application> main menu.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

FAMILY BROWSE SCREEN

</title>



<para>

     This browse screen displays information about a family. The top
     panel shows basic information about the family. The bottom
     panel shows the menu of available commands.  If the database contains
     more than two parents for this family only the first two are displayed.

<screen>
father: Thomas Trask WETMORE IV (1)
  born: 18 December 1949, New London, New London, Connecticut
  died:
mother: Luann Frances GRENDA (2)
  born: 10 July 1949, Pittsburgh, Allegheny, Pennsylvania
  died:
married: 1 August 1970, Governors Island, New York, New York
  child: Anna Vivian Wetmore, b. 1974, Alaska (3)
  child: Marie Margaret WETMORE, b. 1979, Conn. (4)
  child: Thomas Trask WETMORE V, b. 1982, Mass. (5)
_______________________________________________________________________
Please choose an operation:            (pg 1/4)
 e  Edit the family       %s  Add source           r  Remove spouse from
 f  Browse to father      %e  Add event            d  Remove child from
 m  Browse to mother      %o  Add other            x  Swap two children
 c  Browse to children    s  Add spouse to family  ?  Other menu choices
 n  Create new person     a  Add child to family   q  Return to main menu
_______________________________________________________________________
LifeLines -- Family Browse Screen (* toggles menu)

</screen>
</para>



<para>

<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit the family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Edit the family's record. <application>LifeLines</application>
     writes the record to a file and puts you into an editor to
     edit the file. When you return from the editor,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to confirm the
     update; the family is changed only if you do so.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>f</keycap> <action>Browse to father.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the father/husband of the family, switching to
     person browse screen. If the father is not there, there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef>
       </glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap><action>Browse to mother.</action>
         </glossterm>

     <glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to the mother/wife of the family, switching to person
     browse screen. If the mother is not there, there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>c</keycap> <action>Browse to children.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to a child in the family, switching to the person
     browse screen. If the family has more than one child,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify a
     specific child.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>n</keycap> <action>Create new person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Create and add a new person to the
     database. <application>LifeLines</application> creates a
     record template and puts you into the screen editor to edit
     the record. When you return from the editor,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to confirm the
     operation. If you do, the new person is added to the
     database. If not, the new person is not added. In both cases
     the display does not change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>s</keycap> <action>Add spouse to family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Add a spouse to the
     family. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the new spouse. If the command you ran just before
     the s command were the n command,
     <application>LifeLines</application> guesses that the new
     spouse will be the person just
     created. <application>LifeLines</application> asks if this is
     the case, and if so, makes that person the second spouse in
     the family. If not, <application>LifeLines</application> asks
     you to identify the other spouse.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>a</keycap> <action>Add child to family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Add a child to the
     family. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the new child. If the command you ran just before the
     a command were the n command,
     <application>LifeLines</application> guesses that the new
     child will be the person just
     created. <application>LifeLines</application> asks if this is
     the case, and if so, adds that child to the family. If not,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the
     child. If the family already has children,
     <application>LifeLines</application> also asks where to place
     the new child in the family.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>r</keycap> <action>Remove spouse from.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Remove a parent/spouse from the
     family. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the person, and if you do, removes him or her. The
     person is not removed from the database.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>d</keycap> <action>Remove child from.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Remove a child from the
     family. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the child should, and if you do, removes the child
     from the family. The person is not removed from the database.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>x</keycap> <action>Swap two children.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Swap (change the chronological order) of any two children in
     the family.  <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify the two children and then swaps them.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>t</keycap> <action>Enter family tandem.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     This command takes you to the tandem family browse
     screen. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to
     identify a second family, and then takes you to the tandem
     family screen, displaying both the two families.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>b</keycap> <action>Browse to persons.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Browse to a new person or list of persons. You can identify a
     person or list by name, by key, or by list name. If you
     successfully identify a new person or persons you will switch
     into the person or list browse screens.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>z</keycap> <action>Browse to person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Zip browse to a new person.
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify a
     person by name or key value, and if you do, browses to that
     person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Return to the <application>LifeLines</application> main menu.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

TANDEM PERSON BROWSE MODE

</title>



<para>

     The tandem person browse screen displays information about two
     persons. Its main use it to support the person merging
     operation. The top two panels show two persons in the format
     used in the person and list screen displays. The bottom panel
     gives the menu of available commands. For example:


<screen>
  person: Thomas Trask WETMORE Sr (25)
  born: 13 March 1866, St. Mary's Bay, Digby, Nova Scotia
  died: 17 February 1947, New London, New London, Connecticut
  father: Daniel Lorenzo WETMORE, b. 1821, N.S., d. 1903, Conn. (48)
  mother: Mary Ann DOTY, b. 1824, N.S., d. 1897, Conn. (59)
  spouse: Margaret Ellen KANEEN, b. 1855, Eng., d. 1900, Conn. (26)
______________________________________________________________________
person: Thomas Trask WETMORE IV (1)
  born: 18 December 1949, New London, New London, Connecticut
  died:
  father: Thomas Trask WETMORE III, b. 1925, Conn. (6)
  mother: Joan Marie HANCOCK, b. 1928, Conn. (7)
  spouse: Luann Frances GRENDA, m. 1970, N.Y. (2)
______________________________________________________________________
Please choose an operation:
 e Edit top person    s Browse top spouse/s   a Add family
 t Browse to top      c Browse top children   j Merge bottom to top
 f Browse top father  b Browse to persons     x Switch top/bottom
 m Browse top mother  d Copy top to bottom    q Return to main menu
______________________________________________________________________
LifeLines - Two Person Browse Screen
</screen>


</para>



<para>

<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit top person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Edit the top person's
     record. <application>LifeLines</application> writes the record
     to a file, and puts you in the screen editor to edit the
     file. When you return from the editor,
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to confirm the
     update; the person is changed only if you do so.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>t</keycap> <action>Browse to top.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Switch to the person display with the top person as current person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>f</keycap> <action>Browse top father.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Replace the top person with his/her father.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap> <action>Browse top mother.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Replace the top person with his/her mother.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>s</keycap> <action>Browse top spouse/s.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Replace the the top person with his/her spouse. If the person
     has more than one spouse, <application>LifeLines</application>
     asks you to identify one.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>c</keycap> <action>Browse top children.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Replace the top person with one of his/her children. If the person has more
than one child, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the one.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>b</keycap> <action>Browse to persons.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Browse to a new person or list of persons. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify a new
person or persons by name, key or list name, and then does as described in the section on identifying a
person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>d</keycap> <action>Copy top to bottom.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Copy the top person into the bottom person. A new person is not created; the same
person is displayed twice.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>a</keycap> <action>Add family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Create a new family record; <application>LifeLines</application> assumes the two displayed persons are to become
the spouses/parents in the new family; they must be of opposite sex.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>j</keycap> <action>Merge bottom to top.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Merge the bottom person into the top person. <application>LifeLines</application> combines the two person
records and places you in the screen editor to edit the combined record. When you are done, if you
confirm the operation, <application>LifeLines</application> removes the bottom person from the database, and the top person is
given the combined record. See the section on merging.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>x</keycap> <action>Switch top/bottom.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Swap the two persons in the display.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Return to the <application>LifeLines</application> main menu.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

TANDEM FAMILY BROWSE MODE

</title>



<para>

The tandem family browse screen displays information about two families. Its main use it to support the
family merging operation.The top two panels provide information about the two families you are
browsing, and the bottom panel holds the menu of available commands. For example:
<screen>
father: Thomas Trask WETMORE IV (1)
  born: 18 December 1949, New London, New London, Connecticut
mother: Luann Frances GRENDA (2)
  born: 10 July 1949, Pittsburgh, Allegheny, Pennsylvania
married: 1 August 1970, Governors Island, New York, New York
  child: Anna Vivian WETMORE, b. 1974, Alaska (3)
__________________________________________________________________
father: Thomas Trask WETMORE III (6)
  born: 26 October 1925, New London, New London, Connecticut
wife: Joan Marie Hancock (7)
  born: 6 June 1928, New London, New London, Connecticut
married: 5 February 1949, New London, New London, Connecticut
  child: Thomas Trask WETMORE IV, b. 1949, Conn. (1)
__________________________________________________________________
Please choose an operation:            (pg 1/3)
 e  Edit top person       m  Browse to mothers     )b Scroll bottom down
 t  Browse to top         (t Scroll top up         (( Scroll both up
 b  Browse to bottom      )t Scroll top down       ?  Other menu choices
 f  Browse to fathers     (b Scroll bottom up      q  Return to main menu
__________________________________________________________________
LifeLines -- Two Family Browse Screen (* toggles menu)
</screen>


</para>



<para>

<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit top family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command lets you edit the top family's record. <application>LifeLines</application> writes the record into
a file, and then puts you into an editor to edit that information. When you return from the editor,
<application>LifeLines</application> asks you whether you are sure you want to update the family in the database. The family
is changed only if you answer yes.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>t</keycap> <action>Browse to top.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Change to the family browse screen with the top family the current family.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>b</keycap> <action>Browse to bottom.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Change to the single family browse screen with the bottom family the current
family.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>f</keycap> <action>Browse to fathers.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Change to the tandem person screen with the fathers of the two
families as the two persons.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap> <action>Browse to mothers.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Change to the tandem person screen with the mothers of the two
families as the two persons.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>(t</keycap> <action>Scroll top up.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>)t</keycap> <action>Scroll top down.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>(b</keycap> <action>Scroll bottom up.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>)b</keycap> <action>Scroll bottom down.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>((</keycap> <action>Scroll both up.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>))</keycap> <action>Scroll both down.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>#</keycap> <action>Toggle childnos.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>(1-9)</keycap> <action>Browse to child.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

TODO

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>j</keycap> <action>Merge bottom to top.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Merge the bottom family into the top family. <application>LifeLines</application> combines the two
family records and places you in the screen editor to edit the combined record. When you are done, if
you confirm the operation, <application>LifeLines</application> deletes the bottom family from the database, and the top
family is given the combined record. See the section on merging.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>x</keycap> <action>Switch top/bottom.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Swap the two families in the display.

</para>

<para>
   [There are some more miscellaneous commands available on the menus.]
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Return to the <application>LifeLines</application> main menu.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

PEDIGREE BROWSE MODE

</title>



<para>

The pedigree browse screen displays a four-generation pedigree for the current person. The top panel
holds the pedigree, and the bottom panel holds the menu of available commands. For example:
<screen>
                  John WETMORE [1755-1848] (32)
            Daniel Van Cott WETMORE [1791-1881] (41)
                  Anna VAN COTT [1757-1802] (33)
      Daniel Lorenzo WETMORE [1821-1903] (48)
                  Thomas TRASK [-1836] (81)
            Hannah TRASK [1797-1829] (46)
                  Susannah PORTER [1754-] (82)
Thomas Trask WETMORE Sr [1866-1947] (25)
                  Samuel DOTY [1759-] (501)
            Samuel DOTY [1787-] (74)
                  Hephzibah PORTER [1764-1853] (502)
      Mary Ann DOTY [1827-1897] (59)
                  Nathan SAVERY [1748-1826] (510)
            Lydia SAVERY [1806-] (75)
                  Deidamia SABEAN [1765-1845] (511)
__________________________________________________________________
Please choose an operation:
 e Edit the person   m Browse to mother    g Browse to family
 i Browse to person  s Browse to spouse/s  b Browse to persons
 f Browse to father  c Browse to children  q Return to main menu
__________________________________________________________________
LifeLines - Pedigree Browse Mode</screen>

</para>



<para>

<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit the person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Edit the current person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>i</keycap> <action>Browse to person.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Change to the person display mode with the current person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>f</keycap> <action>Browse to father.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Browse to the father of the current person, shifting the pedigree one
generation back. If the father is not in the database, there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap> <action>Browse to mother.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Browse to the mother of the current person, shifting the pedigree one
generation back. If the mother is not in the database, there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>s</keycap> <action>Browse to spouse/s.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Browse to a spouse of the current person, shifting the display to the pedigree of
that person. If the current person has more than one spouse, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the spouse;
if the person has no spouse there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>c</keycap> <action>Browse to children.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Browse to a child of the current person, shifting the pedigree one generation
forward. If the current person has more than one child, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the child; if
the person has no children there is no change.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>g</keycap> <action>Browse to family.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Change to the family display; the family will be the one that the current person
belongs to as spouse or parent. If there are more than one, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the proper
one.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>b</keycap> <action>Browse to persons.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Browse to another person or list of persons; if you identify a single person the
display remains in the pedigree display; if you identify more than one person the display changes to
the list browse mode.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

Leave the pedigree browsing mode and return to the main menu.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</para>


</sect1>


<sect1>


<title>
SEARCH MENU
</title>

<para>
If you choose Search database from the main menu, <application>LifeLines</application> displays the search menu:
<screen>
How would you like to find a record?
  v Review visit history (12 records)
  c Review change history (3 records)
  f Full database scan
  q Return to previous menu
</screen>
The first two items will depend on your previous activity.  If you have
browsed to individuals or family records in the database,
the first item will appear similar to what's shown above,
if you haven't it will just contain a note that the visit history is empty.
The second item will appear similar to what's shown above if you
have changed individual records in this session 
with <application>LifeLines</application>, otherwise it will contain
a note that the change history is empty.
</para>
<para>
Selecting a non-empty visit history or change history will bring up a list
of individuals (or families) that are in the history, allowing you to
browse to that individual or family. 
</para>
<para>
If you choose Full database scan off the search menu, 
<application>LifeLines</application> displays the fullscan menu.
<screen>
What scan type?
  f  Full name scan
  n  Name fragment (whitespace-delimited) scan
  r  Refn scan
  q  Return to previous menu
</screen>
The first two items on this menu allow you to search all the NAME
records in the current database.
If you choose Full name scan you are prompted for a 
search pattern and then <application>LifeLines</application> searches for all 
the individual NAME records whose value matches the pattern supplied.
If you choose the Name fragment scan, you will be prompted for a 
search pattern and then <application>LifeLines</application> will search for
whitespace delimited words within individual NAME records that match the
pattern supplied.
</para>
<sect2>
<title>
Search Patterns
</title>
<para>
The pattern supplied to the search commands is used to match against
the names in the database.  The following characters have special meaning
when used in a pattern:
<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='none'>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<colspec colwidth='0.5in'></colspec>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>?</entry>
<entry>Matches any single character</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>*</entry>
<entry>
Matches zero or more occurrences of any character
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>SUB</entry>
<entry>
a control Z (^Z) is similar to '*', this matches zero
or more occurences of any characters other than '.'.
(of course you probably can't type this on unix)
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>[ab]</entry>
<entry>
A set of characters enclosed in square brackets
matches the single characters listed between the
brackets.  If the dash '-' character is to be included,
it must immediately follow the opening bracket '['.
If the closing bracket ']' character is to be included,
it must be preceded by a quote '`'.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>[a-z]</entry>
<entry>
Matches a single character in the range 'a' to 'z'.
Ranges and sets may be combined within the same set of
brackets.
</entry>
</row>


<row>
<entry>!R</entry>
<entry>
Matches a single character not in the range 'R'.
If range 'R' includes the dash '-' character, the dash
must immediately follow the '!'.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>!</entry>
<entry>
Makes the following pattern match
any string except those what it would normally match.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>QUOTE</entry>
<entry>
(On DOS this is `, on UNIX it is \)
Makes the next character a regular (nonspecial)
character.
Note that to match the quote character itself, it must
be quoted.
Note that this character must be escaped if used within
string constants ("\\").
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</para>
<para>
Upper and lower case alphabetic characters are considered identical,
i.e., 'a' and 'A' match each other.
(What constitutes a lowercase letter depends on the current locale
settings.)
</para>
<para>
Spaces and control characters (other than control z) are treated as normal 
characters,
</para>

<para>
As an example, consider the following NAME record:
<programlisting>
1 NAME <userinput>John /Smith/</userinput>
</programlisting>
When doing a full name search, the value searched is the complete gedcom name 
value including the slashes used to delimit the surname.
in order to have a match, the search pattern
must match the slashes.  Thus

<programlisting>
*smith
</programlisting>
will not match this name, whereas
<programlisting>
*smith/
</programlisting>
will match.
</para>

<para>
When doing a name fragment search, the slashes are removed from the surname
before trying to match the name, thus
<programlisting>
smith
smi*
joh*
*hn
</programlisting>
will all match this NAME record.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>

<title>
ADD OPERATION
</title>



<para>

If you choose the add operation from the main menu, <application>LifeLines</application> displays the add menu:
<screen>
What do you want to add?
  p Person - add new person to the database
  f Family - create family record from one or two spouses
  c Child - add a child to an existing family
  s Spouse - add a spouse to an existing family
  q Quit - return to the previous menu
</screen>


</para>



<para>

These operations work in a straightforward way. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you the necessary questions, and lets
you cancel at any time. The operations provided by this menu are also available from the browsing
modes, and are often easier to perform there.

</para>




</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

DELETE OPERATION

</title>



<para>

If you choose the delete operation at the main menu, <application>LifeLines</application> displays the delete menu:
<screen>
What do you want to delete?
  c Child - remove a child from his/her family
  s Spouse - remove a spouse from a family
  p Person - remove a person completely
  q Quit - return to the previous menu
</screen>


</para>



<para>

These operations also work in a straightforward way. <application>LifeLines</application> asks you the necessary questions and
lets you cancel at any time.


</para>



<para>

You may also remove a child from his/her family, or remove a spouse/parent from his/her family,
from the person browsing mode. In both cases, only a relationship is removed, not a person. On the other
hand, the delete menu must be used if you want to completely remove a person from the database; this
cannot be done from the browsing mode.


</para>



<para>

There is no special operation for removing a family record. <application>LifeLines</application> silently removes any family
record that has no parent or child associated with it.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

CODESET CONVERSION

</title>



<para>

     (This section was previously entitled CHARACTER TRANSLATION.)

</para>

<para>

     The intention is that you need only specify the internal codeset for
     each database you create (and this step may be automated via the NewDbProps
     property), and all else works pretty well without tuning. That is,
     lifelines tries to guess the correct codeset for your environment (including
     guessing the console and windows codesets when operating under MS-Windows,
     which it should do fairly well).

</para>

<para>

     However, you may encounter situations where you wish to alter the codeset
     behavior, or the codeset conversion is not operating correctly (in which case
     we hope you will report the problem to the mailing list and/or sourceforge
     bugs list).

</para>

<para>

     There are two ways to amend codeset conversion. The first method is by
     changing configuration variables. For example, if you wish to generate an
     HTML report of all your data, which includes names in Russian (in Cyrillic
     letters), for your cousin, and you know that your cousin's computer has no
     font for Cyrillic letters, you might wish to temporarily adjust your
     report output codeset so that you will get interpolated ASCII letters for
     the Russian letters. You could do this by temporarily altering the
     configuration variable ReportCodesetOut to be "ASCII" (actually, if any of
     your data has characters in it that are reserved in HTML, such as the less
     than sign, or the ampersand, you would probaby want "ASCII//HTML").

</para>

<para>

     The second way to change codeset conversion, and the only way in lifelines
     3.0.6, is to edit the embedded character translation tables, in which you
     actually specify the letters you want converted, letter by letter, and how
     you want them converted.  This method, unlike the first, even works in
     databases with no specified internal codeset.  </para>

<para>

If you choose the modify character translation tables operation from the main menu, <application>LifeLines</application> displays
the character translation menu:
<screen>
Which character mapping do you want to edit?
   e Editor to Internal mapping
   m Internal to Editor mapping
   i GEDCOM to Internal mapping
   x Internal to GEDCOM mapping
   d Internal to Display mapping
   r Internal to Report mapping
   q Return to main menu
</screen>


</para>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> can do codeset conversion in changing
     text from one form to another, and lifelines supports five different
     forms.

</para>



<para>

</para>
<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm>internal</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

for records in the database

</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>editor</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
for records being edited
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>display</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
for records being displayed
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>report</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
for records written to output file
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>GEDCOM</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
for records read in from or written out to GEDCOM
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>


<para>

     When converting text from one form to another
     <application>LifeLines</application> normally uses iconv conversion, and
     codesets specified in configuration variables. This may be augmented by
     codeset translation or extension using the text conversion (*.tt) files in
     the tt subdirectory. To use the tables in the tt subdirectory,
     you need to set
     the property "TTPATH" in your <application>LifeLines</application>
     configuration file to the path of the tt directory.  There are two types
     of files in this directory. 
     
</para>
<para>
     
     Files of the form &lt;codeset&gt;_&lt;codeset1&gt;.tt convert from one 
     codeset to another. For example, CP1250_UTF-8.tt can be used to convert
     characters in codeset CP1250 to their representations in UTF-8.
     
</para>
<para>

     Files of the form &lt;codeset&gt;__&lt;subcodeset&gt;.tt apply a
     conversion within the codeset, for example, UTF-8__html.tt is a
     sub-conversion that converts UTF-8 characters that have special escape
     codes within html to those special codes.  For example, specifing the
     report codeset to be UTF-8//html will apply the html sub-conversion to
     all the data being written.  Probably not what you really wanted.
     See the report language function convertcode() in the reportmanual for
     details.

</para>
<para>
     
     If your system lacks iconv, or you need more specialized
     conversion than provided with iconv, you may either write a text
     conversion file (a tt file), or you may edit one of the in-database
     translation tables.
 
</para>
<para>

     The in-database translation tables convert between forms (as listed
     above). Every translation table converts either to the internal form, or
     from the internal form. That is, the internal form is used as an
     intermediate step in all operations. There are six supported translation
     tables.  The following table shows the six tables and describes when they
     are applied:
     
</para>

<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm>internal to editor</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
when converting from internal, database form to editor form
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>editor to internal</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
when converting from editor form back to internal, database form
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> to internal</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
when reading <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> input records and writing them to 
database
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>internal to <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
when writing internal database records to external <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> file
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry>
<glossentry><glossterm>internal to display</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
when displaying a record in a browsing mode display screen
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>internal to report</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
when writing internal database records to external report file
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

<para>

After you select a translation table you are placed in the editor to edit the table. Translation tables are
made up of lines that look like:
<synopsis><replaceable>pattern</replaceable> <replaceable>pattern</replaceable></synopsis>
where a tab separates the patterns. Each pattern is an arbitrary sequence of verbatim <acronym>ASCII</acronym> characters
and escape sequences. Translation occurs by finding all occurrences that match left patterns and
replacing them with the corresponding right patterns.

</para>



<para>
There are five escape mechanisms used in patterns:
</para>

<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm>#nnn</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
nnn is a decimal character value
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>$hh</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
hh is a hexadecimal character value
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>\ #</glossterm><glossdef>
<!-- note above has extra space between \ and # - without this 
     conversion to pdf gets confused openjade does some tex processing...
-->

<para>
represents the # character
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>\$</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
represents the $ character
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>\\</glossterm><glossdef>
<para>
represents the \ character
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

<para>

     It is possible, and desirable, to provide a short name for
     the translation table, using the "##!name: " command. An 
     example would be

</para>

<programlisting>
##!name: UTF-8 to latex
</programlisting>

<para>

     Naming the translation table is desirable because these 
     names are displayed, at least in part and if they fit, on
     the translation table menu.

</para>

<para>

     It is possible to format the file using a character other than
     tab as the separator between source and destination code. To do
     requires using the "##!sep" command. Those exact six characters
     must begin the line, and then the next character is the new
     separator for all following lines. For clarity, this should only
     occur once, and near the top of the file before any actual
     translation lines, and a fairly clear separator should be used
     (e.g., the equal sign "=").

</para>

<para>

     Any line which is blank, or which begins with two hash marks (##), is
     ignored. Therefore, comments begin with two hash marks.

</para>

<para>

     For advanced users, it is possible to mix different types of 
     conversion, for example iconv conversion and also translation
     table conversion, in the same form step. For example, it is possible
     to convert internal database text (internal form) first via the
     "internal to GEDCOM" in-database translation table, and then via
     the iconv conversion from configured internal codeset to configured
     GEDCOM codeset. In-database translation tables are always applied
     in the internal codeset, so when converting to the internal form,
     they are applied after iconv and/or tt conversions, and when
     converting from internal form, they are applied first.

</para>

<para>

     An example of adding a mixin in-database translation table might
     be to escape certain characters which are control characters
     to an output computer language, e.g., latex. One could create an
     "Internal to Report" mapping in UTF-8 (if the database is internally
     UTF-8) to escape any characters that may occur in place names or
     textual descriptions and inadvertently cause grief in latex
     processing.

</para>

<para>

     However, in this case, one could also write a tt file to achieve
     the same results, and be shared across databases, by naming it, eg,
     UTF-8__latex.tt. The double underscore ("__") signifies that this
     is a conversion to be applied to text which is in UTF-8, and to 
     trigger lifelinesn to use this, one must specify a report codeset
     such as "UTF-8//latex" (if UTF-8 output is desired, but with the
     latex conversion first applied), or "ISO-8859-1//latex" (if 
     ISO-8859-1 output is desired, but with the latex conversion first
     applied).

</para>

</sect1>



<sect1> 

<title>

MISCELLANEOUS UTILITIES

</title>



<para>

If you choose the miscellaneous utilities operation,
<application>LifeLines</application> displays the utilities menu:
<screen>
What utility do you want to perform?
  s Save the database in a GEDCOM file
  r Read in data from a GEDCOM file
  R  Pick a GEDCOM file and read in
  k Find a person's key value
  i Identify a person from key value
  d Show database statistics
  m Show memory statistics
  e Edit the place abbreviation file
  o Edit the user options file
  c  Character set options
  q Return to the main menu
</screen>


</para>


<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>s</keycap> <action>Save the database in a GEDCOM file.</action></glossterm><glossdef>
<para>

This command saves the complete <application>LifeLines</application> database in a
<acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> file. All person, family, event, source and user-defined records are stored. This command
may be used to periodically back up your database. When you use this command, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you
for the name of the file. If you have defined the <envar>LLARCHIVE</envar> shell variable, <application>LifeLines</application> will store
the file in the directory named in the variable.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>r</keycap> <action>Read in data from a GEDCOM file.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command allows you restore a complete database from a
<acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> file. When you select this command, <application>LifeLines</application> asks you for the name of the <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> file.
This command can also be used to import data from a <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> file to an existing database. When
<application>LifeLines</application> performs this command, it first reads the entire <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> file and checks it for validity.
If there are problems in the file, <application>LifeLines</application> describes them, writing them to the file err.log, and does
not add any records to the database. If there are no problems, <application>LifeLines</application> adds all the records found in
the file to the database (only header and trailer records are not stored in the database).

</para>
<para>
Normally, <application>LifeLines</application> will replace the XREF's (the
identifiers for individuals, families, sources, notes, etc.) in the
<acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> with its own.
These identifiers are reserved by the <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> for internal
use of genealogy programs.  However, if the identifiers are compatible with
<application>LifeLines</application> internal representation and there are no
conflicts with existing identifiers, <application>LifeLines</application> will
ask you if you want to perserve the identifiers in the 
<acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> 
file rather than assign new values.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>k</keycap> <action>Find a person's key value.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command finds the internal key value of a person.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>i</keycap> <action>Identify a person from key value.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command identifies the person that has a particular internal
key value.

</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>d</keycap> <action>Show database statistics.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command summarizes the contents of the current database. It
displays the number of person, family, source, event and other records in the database.

</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>m</keycap> <action>Show memory statistics.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command is used by the author for debugging.

</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap> <action>Edit the place abbreviation file.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     This command allows you to edit the place abbreviations
     file. This file defines the abbreviations that are used by
     <application>LifeLines</application> when it creates lists of
     persons for you to select from. Each line in the file has the
     format:<synopsis><replaceable>word</replaceable>:<replaceable>
     abbr </replaceable></synopsis>where word is a word to be
     abbreviated, and abbr is its abbreviation. The word and its
     abbreviation are separated by a colon. For example:

<example>

<title>
Example of using abbreviations
</title>

<literallayout>Connecticut:Conn.
Massachusetts:Mass.
Nova Scotia:N.S.</literallayout></example>

</para>



<para>

When <application>LifeLines</application> constructs lists of persons for you to select from, it looks up the last component of
certain <structfield>PLAC</structfield> lines in this file, and if it finds that component, replaces it with its abbreviation.

</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>o</keycap>
<action>Edit the user options file.</action>
</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This command allows you to edit the user options file. The user options file
is a record kept in the database that holds user selectable options. Each
option has a name and a string value. Each line in the options file has the
format:<synopsis><replaceable>option</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable></synopsis>
where option is the name of an option and value is the option's string value.
If the value is more than one line long, then the last character in each
non-final line must be a backslash. The escapes \n and \t are also recognized
in version 3.0.7 and better (to represent a carriage return and a tab, respectively).
These (\n and \t) are primarily for use in custom record templates.
In version 3.0.14 there are 39 options. Note that all of these may also be specified in
the configuration file, to apply to all databases, but if specified in
both places, the entry in the database (user options table) governs.
For more information, see the sample configuration file; each option is preceded
by a brief explanation.

</para>

<para>
The list of options can be found in the section 'System and User Properties'
below.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

<para>

For example if you would like to replace the default person
record template with the following:

<example>

<title>
Example of replacing the default person record template
</title>

<programlisting>

  0 INDI
  1 NAME //
  1 SEX</programlisting></example>
you would edit the user option file to contain:<example>

<title>
Example of replaced default person record template
</title>

<literallayout>INDIREC=0 INDI\
  1 NAME //\
  1 SEX</literallayout>
</example>

or, using the \n escape so as to keep the entry on one line:<example>

<title>
Example of replaced single line default person record template
</title>

<literallayout>INDIREC=0 INDI\n1 NAME //\n1 SEX</literallayout>
</example>

</para>

<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm><keycap>q</keycap> <action>Return to main menu.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
This command returns you to the main menu.
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>


</sect1>

<sect1>

<title>
IMPORT ERRORS
</title>

<para>
Errors generated during a GEDCOM import are logged to a file,
by default named errs.log. 
</para>
<para>
A number of errors are related to having an incorrect XREF value.
An XREF is the internal name used to Identify a family, individual, note,
source or other record.  An XREF is bracked by two @ signs.  As an example
</para>
<programlisting>  0 @F6@ FAM
  1 HUSB @I25@
  1 WIFE @I26@
  1 CHIL @I17@</programlisting>
<para>
Here F6 is the internal name of this family.  The family refers
to other individuals by specifing their XREF values.  Also I25, I26 and I17
are XREF values of individuals. 
</para>
<para>
XREF values used within <application>LifeLines</application> are totally under
the control of <application>LifeLines</application>.
The values that are used are always of the form, a single letter, followed by
a number.  However, when importing a gedcom
<application>LifeLines</application> should accept almost
anything as an XREF, converting it to what is needed for internal use.
For the curious, the letters that <application>LifeLines</application> uses
are I for Individual, F for Family, S for Source, E for Events, and X for
other records.

</para>
<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm>Bad NAME syntax.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     A level 1 NAME record must have a value, and the value must not be a pointer, and may 
     have no more than two slashes.
</para>

<example><title>
Example of bad NAME syntax (too many slashes in this case)
</title>
<programlisting>  0 @I99@ INDI
  1 NAME Mary /Smith/ nee /Jones/
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry>
<glossterm>Family F13 has an incorrect key.</glossterm>
<glossdef><para></para></glossdef></glossentry>
<glossentry>
<glossterm>Person XYZ has an incorrect key: skipped.</glossterm>
<glossdef>

<para>

     The XREF values must be unique.  These error messages are
     generated if a XREF is found to refer to two different records.
     For example, the XREF for a family is the same as one for an individual.

</para>

<example><title>
Example of XREF XYZ being defined twice
</title>
<programlisting>  0 @XYZ@ INDI
  1 NAME Mary /Smith/ nee /Jones/
  0 @XYZ@ FAM
  1 HUSB @I48@
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Person defined here has no name.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Each INDI record must have at least one level 1 NAME record, if the 
     configuration option RequireNames is non-zero.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Person INDI_XYZ is multiply defined: skipped.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     No XREF value of an INDI may be reused.  This message indicates that
     INDI_XYZ has been used to identify two different persons.

</para>

<example><title>
Example of person multiply defined
</title>
<programlisting>  0 @INDI_XYZ@ INDI
  1 NAME John /Smith/
  0 @INDI_XYZ@ INDI
  1 NAME Jack /Smith/
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>The family defined here has no key.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Each FAM record must have an XREF value.
     (The XREF is the letters between "0" and "FAM".)

</para>

<example><title>
Example of family record missing key
</title>
<programlisting>  0 FAM
  1 HUSB @I1@
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>Family F123 is referred to but
not defined.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     A FAMS or FAMC record on an Individual refers to a family
     but there is no FAM record with that XREF.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>The person defined here has no key: skipped.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Each INDI record must have an XREF value.
     (The XREF is the letters between "0" and "INDI".)

</para>

<example><title>
Example of person record missing key
</title>
<programlisting>  0 INDI
  1 NAME John /Smith/
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>This line has a level number that is too large.</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     A child level must be one higher than its parent level.

</para>

<example><title>
Example of level number which is too high
</title>
<programlisting>  0 @I99@ INDI
  1 NAME //
  3 NOTE name is missing
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm>This FAMS line is missing a
value field (INDI I99).</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

   Lineage-linking tags must have a value, including tags FAMC, FAMS, FATH, MOTH, HUSB, WIFE, CHIL.

</para>

<example><title>
Example of lineage-linking line which is missing required value
</title>
<programlisting>  0 @I99@ INDI
  1 NAME John /Smith/
  2 FAMS
</programlisting></example>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</sect1>

<sect1>



<title>

HANDLING SOURCE, EVENT AND USER-DEFINED RECORDS

</title>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> supports source, event
     and other, user-defined record types.  You can access these
     features in two ways: either through the x operation from the
     main menu, or via commands in the individual and family browse
     screens.  The first approach might be most convenient when you
     are solely working with these record types.  The second makes
     it easier to work with source, event and user-defined records
     in parallel with your person and family records; this can be
     useful for instance when you want to create references from
     your person and family record to your source, event and user
     defined records as you create them, and to view and edit
     records that you have referenced from within a person or
     family record.

</para>

<para>

     Using the first of these two possibilities
     <application>LifeLines</application> displays the following
     menu:

<screen>
What activity do you want to perform?

  s  Browse source records
  e  Browse event records
  x  Browse other records
  1  Add a source record to the database
  2  Edit source record from the database
  3  Add an event record to the database
  4  Edit event record from the database
  5  Add an other record to the database
  6  Edit other record from the database
  q  Return to main menu
</screen>

     Using the second variant (from the person and family browse
     screens), the following six commands are available. The first
     three are described alongside with their counterparts in the x
     menu (they do mostly, but not entirely, the same things); the
     last three are described separately:

<screen>
  %s  Add source
  %e  Add event
  %o  Add other
</screen>

<screen>
  $s  List sources
  $n  List notes
  $$  List references
</screen>

</para>



<para>

     The handling of source, event and user-defined records in
     <application>LifeLines</application> is still in
     development. For example, sources cannot yet be searched by
     REFN or be deleted.

</para>

<glosslist><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>s</keycap>
<action>Browse source records.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
This will bring up a list of all source records by number, showing
REFN, title, and author for each. A record may be selected
from this list to edit.
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>e</keycap>
<action>Browse event records.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
This will bring up a list of all event records by number. As of
yet this does not display any information about each event.
(Suggestions as to how to summarize events are welcome).
A record may be selected from this list to edit.
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>x</keycap>
<action>Browse other records.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
This will bring up a list of all other records by number,
showing the 0 level line as summary. A record may be selected
from this list to edit.
</para>

     </glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>1</keycap>
     <action>Add a source record to the
     database.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     This operation (or alternatively <keycap>%s</keycap> from the
     person, family or auxiliary browse screens) is used to add a
     new source record to the database.
     <application>LifeLines</application> creates a template source
     and puts you in the screen editor to edit the template. The
     default template is:

<programlisting>  0 SOUR
  1 REFN
  1 TITL <replaceable>Title</replaceable>
  1 AUTH <replaceable>Author</replaceable>

</programlisting>

</para>



<para>

     Do not change the <structfield>0 SOUR</structfield>
     line. Otherwise you may edit this record any way you like. The
     <structfield>1 REFN</structfield> line is a special line you
     can use to give the source a symbolic name that can be used in
     other records to refer to the source record. See the section
     on using <structfield>REFN</structfield> values. Because many
     sources have a title and an author, the default template has
     these lines. You may adjust the source template via the
     SOURREC user option (either at the database level, via the
     user options, or globally, via the configuration file). Here
     is how I recorded one of the sources in my database:

<example>

<title>
Example of a source record
</title>

<programlisting>0 SOUR
  1 REFN <userinput>jcw</userinput>
  1 TITL <userinput>The Wetmore Family of America, and its Collateral Branches: with</userinput>
    2 CONT <userinput>Genealogical, Biographical, and Historical Notices</userinput>
  1 AUTH <userinput>James Carnahan Wetmore</userinput>
  1 PUBL
    2 DATE <userinput>1861</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>Albany, New York</userinput>
    2 INST <userinput>Munsell and Rowland</userinput>
    2 ADDR <userinput>78 State Street</userinput></programlisting></example>

</para>

<para>

     The add source command in the x menu is equivalent to the
     <keycap>%s</keycap> command available in the person or family
     browse screen, in terms of entering the source record; after
     saving the source record though, there is one significant
     difference, in that that you then are presented with the
     following prompt (also, the key value of the new record is
     displayed in the status bar at this point):
</para>

<screen>
Please choose from the following options:
  1: Insert xref automatically at bottom of current record.
  2: Edit current record now to add xref manually.
  3: Browse new record (without adding xref).
  4: Return to current record (without adding xref).

 Commands:   j Move down     k Move up    i Select     q Quit
</screen>

     <para>

     The four options perform the following actions:

     </para>

     <para>

     1: LifeLines adds a reference to the new source record at the
     bottom of the person or family record that was visible in the
     display screen when you prompted LifeLines to create the new
     source record.

     </para>

     <para>

     2: LifeLines will open the person or family record that was
     visible in the display screen when you prompted LifeLines to
     create the new source record, so that you can manually enter a
     reference to the newly created source record (perhaps as a
     source reference to an event that you are planning to add).

     </para>

     <para>

     3: LifeLines lets you browse (and optionally reopen for
     editing) your newly added source record.

     </para>

     <para>

     4: You are returned to the person or family record that was
     visible in the display screen when you prompted LifeLines to
     create the new source record. No reference is added to the new
     record.

     </para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>2</keycap> <action>Edit source record from the database.</action></glossterm>
<glossdef>

<para>

Use this operation to edit an existing source record already in
the database. When you select this operation
<application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify a source:
<screen>
Which source record do you want to edit?
enter key or refn:
</screen>


</para>



<para>

Identify a source by entering its key value, with or without the leading S, or by entering its <structfield>REFN</structfield>
value. <application>LifeLines</application> retrieves the record and puts you in the editor with the record.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>3</keycap> <action>Add an event record to the database.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

This operation (or alternatively <keycap>%e</keycap> from the person,
family or auxiliary browse screens) adds a new event record to the
database.  <application>LifeLines</application> creates a template
event and puts you in the screen editor to edit the template. The
default template is:
<programlisting>0 EVEN
  1 REFN
  1 DATE
  1 PLAC
  1 INDI
    2 NAME
    2 ROLE
  1 SOUR</programlisting>

</para>

<para>

     You may adjust the event template via the EVENREC user option (either
     at the database level, via the user options, or globally, via the
     configuration file).

</para>

<para>

     Do not change the <structfield>0 EVEN</structfield>
     line. Otherwise you may edit this record any way you like. The
     <structfield>1 REFN</structfield> line allows you to give this
     event a symbolic name you can use when you want to refer to
     this event from other records. See the section on using
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> values. The default template
     suggests that an event has a date, a place, and refers to
     persons in roles with respect to the event. There is far less
     experience with event-based <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym> than
     there is with simple person and family
     <acronym>GEDCOM</acronym>. You may even be wondering why you
     would need event records when you can simply tuck events away
     in person and family records. This is a topic that may get
     covered in an appendix.

</para>

     <para>

     The add event command in the x menu is equivalent to the
     <keycap>%e</keycap> command available in the person or family
     browse screen, in terms of entering the event record; after
     saving the event record though, there is one significant
     difference, in that that you then are presented with the
     following prompt (also, the key value of the new record is
     displayed in the status bar at this point):
</para>

<screen>
Please choose from the following options:
  1: Insert xref automatically at bottom of current record.
  2: Edit current record now to add xref manually.
  3: Browse new record (without adding xref).
  4: Return to current record (without adding xref).

 Commands:   j Move down     k Move up    i Select     q Quit
</screen>

     <para>

     The four options perform the following actions:

     </para>

     <para>

     1: LifeLines adds a reference to the new event record at the
     bottom of the person or family record that was visible in the
     display screen when you prompted LifeLines to create the new
     event record.

     </para>

     <para>

     2: LifeLines will open the person or family record that was
     visible in the display screen when you prompted LifeLines to
     create the new event record, so that you can manually enter a
     reference to the newly created event record.

     </para>

     <para>

     3: LifeLines lets you browse (and optionally reopen for
     editing) your newly added event record.

     </para>

     <para>

     4: You are returned to the person or family record that was
     visible in the display screen when you prompted LifeLines to
     create the new event record. No reference is added to the new
     record.

     </para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>4</keycap> <action>Edit event record from the database.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Use this operation to edit an existing event record from the
     database . When you select this operation
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify an
     event:

<screen>
Which event record do you want to edit?
enter key or refn:
</screen>


</para>



<para>

     You identify a event by entering its key value, with or
     without the leading E, or by entering its
     <structfield>REFN</structfield>
     value. <application>LifeLines</application> retrieves the
     record and places you in the screen editor with the record.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>5</keycap> <action>Add an other record to the database.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     This operation (or alternatively <keycap>%o</keycap> from the
     person, family or auxiliary browse screens) adds a new
     user-defined record to the database.
     <application>LifeLines</application> creates a template and
     puts you in the screen editor to edit the template. The
     default template is

<programlisting>0 XXXX
1 REFN
</programlisting>
</para>



<para>

     Replace <replaceable>XXXX</replaceable> with the tag string
     you select for the type of the new record. You are free to
     choose any tag value except <structfield>INDI</structfield>,
     <structfield>FAM</structfield>,
     <structfield>SOUR</structfield> and
     <structfield>EVEN</structfield>. For example, if you keep
     record information about the ships that your North American
     immigrant ancestors arrived on, you would keep records about
     those ships in your database; the tag
     <structfield>SHIP</structfield> suggests itself for such
     records. The <structfield>1 REFN</structfield> line allows you
     to give this record a symbolic name you can use when you want
     to refer to it from other records. See the section on using
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> values. You may adjust the
     other template via the OTHR user option (either at the database
     level, via the user options, or globally, via the configuration
     file).

</para>

     <para>

     The add other record command in the x menu is equivalent to the
     <keycap>%o</keycap> command available in the person or family
     browse screen, in terms of entering the other record; after
     saving the record though, there is one significant difference,
     in that that you then are presented with the following prompt
     (also, the key value of the new record is displayed in the
     status bar at this point):
</para>

<screen>
Please choose from the following options:
  1: Insert xref automatically at bottom of current record.
  2: Edit current record now to add xref manually.
  3: Browse new record (without adding xref).
  4: Return to current record (without adding xref).

 Commands:   j Move down     k Move up    i Select     q Quit
</screen>

     <para>

     The four options perform the following actions:

     </para>

     <para>

     1: LifeLines adds a reference to the new other record at the
     bottom of the person or family record that was visible in the
     display screen when you prompted LifeLines to create the new
     other record.

     </para>

     <para>

     2: LifeLines will open the person or family record that was
     visible in the display screen when you prompted LifeLines to
     create the new other record, so that you can manually enter a
     reference to the newly created other record (perhaps as a
     note reference to an event that you are planning to add).

     </para>

     <para>

     3: LifeLines lets you browse (and optionally reopen for
     editing) your newly added other record.

     </para>

     <para>

     4: You are returned to the person or family record that was
     visible in the display screen when you prompted LifeLines to
     create the new other record. No reference is added to the new
     record.

     </para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>6</keycap> <action>Edit other record from the database.</action></glossterm><glossdef>

<para>

     Use this operation to edit an existing user-defined record
     from the database. When you select this operation
     <application>LifeLines</application> asks you to identify the
     record:

<screen>
What record do you want to edit?
enter key or refn:
</screen>


</para>

<para>

     You identify a record by entering its key value, with or
     without the leading X, or by entering its
     <structfield>REFN</structfield>
     value. <application>LifeLines</application> retrieves the
     record and places you in the screen editor with the record.

</para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>$s</keycap>
<action>List sources</action></glossterm><glossdef>

     <para>

     This command is available in the person and family browse
     screens. It will bring up a list of all source records that
     are referenced within the currently displayed person or family
     record, by the order they appear in the person/family record,
     showing REFN, title, and author for each. A record may be
     selected from this list to view in the auxiliary browse screen
     (and optionally be edited from there).

     </para>


</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>$n</keycap>
<action>List notes</action></glossterm><glossdef>

     <para>

     This command is available in the person and family browse
     screens. It will bring up a list of all note records that are
     referenced within the currently displayed person or family
     record, by the order they appear in the person/family record,
     showing REFN, title, and author for each. A record may be
     selected from this list to view in the auxiliary browse screen
     (and optionally be edited from there).

     </para>

</glossdef></glossentry><glossentry><glossterm><keycap>$$</keycap>
<action>List all references</action></glossterm><glossdef>

     <para>

     This command is available in the person and family browse
     screens. It will bring up a list of all records that are
     referenced within the currently displayed person or family
     record, by the order they appear in the person/family record,
     showing REFN, title, and author for each. A record may be
     selected from this list to view in the auxiliary browse screen
     (and optionally be edited from there).

     </para>

</glossdef></glossentry></glosslist>

</sect1>



<sect1>

<title>
FAMILY STRUCTURE AND MERGING PERSONS AND FAMILIES
</title>

<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> 3.0.2 has relaxed most of
     restrictions on family structure that were imposed by earlier
     versions. For example, a family record may have more than one
     parent/spouse of the same sex; a person may be a child in more
     than family. This is a controversial issue. Some users insist
     that family relationships should imply biological relatedness,
     and that all other relationships should be handled by
     different means. Others insist that non-traditional families
     (any number of parents/spouses of any sex) should be allowed,
     and that children can be members of more than one family (eg,
     natural family and adoptive
     family). <application>LifeLines</application> no longer takes
     a position on this matter; you are free to set up families any
     way you like; the operations that add spouses and children to
     families no longer check for non-traditional arrangements. It
     is possible that a future release will include a user option
     to either disallow or to ask for confirmation about
     non-traditional relationships.

</para>



<para>

     <application>LifeLines</application> provides features for
     merging persons together and for merging families
     together. The person merging feature is accessed from the
     tandem person browse mode, and the family merging feature is
     accessed from the tandem family browse mode. You browse to the
     two persons or families you want to merge and then use the j
     command. Merging is necessary when you discover that two or
     more person records, or two or more family records, represent
     the same person or family, respectively.

</para>



<para>

     Versions of <application>LifeLines</application> prior to
     3.0.2 required that persons and families meet certain criteria
     before they could be merged. The criteria ensured that the
     merged persons and families would still meet traditional
     family structuring rules. With the relaxation of the
     structuring rules, restrictions on merging have also been
     removed. It is now possible to create non-traditional
     relationships by merging traditional persons and/or
     families. For example, if you merge two persons that happen to
     be children in two different families, the merged person will
     be a child in both families. If you want to maintain only
     traditional relationships in your database you may have to
     makes further to changes to relationships after you complete a
     merge operation.

</para>



</sect1>



<sect1>



<title>

LINKING RECORDS TOGETHER AND USING THE REFN FEATURE

</title>



<para>

     Records in a <application>LifeLines</application> database may
     refer to other records via cross-reference links. The
     lineage-linked references are maintained directly by
     <application>LifeLines</application> through operations found
     in the browsing mode menus.  These references are the links
     from a person to families (<structfield>1 FAMC</structfield>
     and <structfield>1 FAMS</structfield>), and the links from a
     family to persons (<structfield>1 HUSB</structfield>,
     <structfield>1 WIFE</structfield> and <structfield>1
     CHIL</structfield>). Because
     <application>LifeLines</application> maintains these links you
     are not allowed to change these lines when you are editing
     records. There are a couple of seeming exceptions to this
     rule. For example, you may change the order of <structfield>1
     CHIL</structfield> lines in a family record in order to change
     the order of children in a family, and you may change the
     order of <structfield>1 FAMS</structfield> lines in a person
     record to change the order of families the person was a spouse
     or parent in. These operations are allowed because they don't
     affect which person records refer to which family records and
     vice versa.

</para>



<para>

     Besides the lineage-links that are maintained by
     <application>LifeLines</application>, you may place your own
     links in records.  Probably the most common example of this is
     referring events within a person record to the record of the
     information source for the event. For example:


<example>

<title>
Example of referring events from a person record
</title>

<programlisting>0 @I23@ INDI
  1 NAME <userinput>Thomas/Whitmore/</userinput>
  1 BIRT
    2 DATE <userinput>about 1615</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>England</userinput>
    2 SOUR @S3@
...
0 @S3@ SOUR
  1 REFN <userinput>cat</userinput>
  1 TITL <userinput>New England Marriages Prior to 1700</userinput>
  1 AUTH <userinput>Clarence Almon Torrey</userinput>
...</programlisting></example>

</para>



<para>

The <structfield>2 SOUR</structfield> <replaceable>@S3@</replaceable> line in the person record refers to the source record. <application>LifeLines</application> allows any specific
structure within a record (in this case a birth event) to refer to another record. It is not possible to refer
to a specific location within another record, though this may be supported eventually.


</para>



<para>

This example implies that when linking one record to another you must know the key of the target
record (S3 in the example). This is not desirable because internal record keys may change when the
records are exported from one database or imported to another.

</para>



<para>

     Because internal key values are not permanent,
     <application>LifeLines</application> allows you to assign a
     permanent user-defined key to any record in the database using
     the <structfield>1 REFN</structfield> line. The value of this
     line is a string that you choose as your permanent key value
     for the record. When adding a link to a record that has a user
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> key value, you may use that
     value instead of the internal key value. For example, when
     adding the person in the previous example you could edit the
     new record as follows:

<example>

<title>
Example of adding a new person
</title>

<programlisting>0 INDI
  1 NAME <userinput>Thomas/Whitmore/</userinput>
  1 BIRT
    2 DATE <userinput>about 1615</userinput>
    2 PLAC <userinput>England</userinput>
    2 SOUR <userinput>&lt;cat&gt;</userinput></programlisting></example>

</para>



<para>

     Instead of using the actual key value of the source, S3, the
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> value cat was used. The
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> value must be enclosed by
     angle brackets when used this
     way. <application>LifeLines</application> automatically
     replaces the <structfield>REFN</structfield> link with the
     proper internal key value when the record is stored in the
     database.


</para>



<para>

     The <structfield>REFN</structfield> value may also be used
     when searching for person, source, event and user-defined
     records.  You should not add more than one
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> line to a record, and every
     <structfield>REFN</structfield> value should be unique.

</para>

</sect1>


<sect1>



<title>

System and User Properties

</title>

<para>
There are a number of properties that can be specified to customize
the behavior of <application>LifeLines</application>.  These properties can 
be specified in <application>LifeLines</application>
configuration files, in each <application>LifeLines</application> database 
or in some cases by environment variables.
</para>
<para>
System Properties are properties that have a predefined meaning to lifelines,
such as LLEDITOR (see its meaning below).  User Properties typically have no
predefined meanings as they are simply a string that a report looks up in the
property tables.  It can be anything a user desires.  To simplify report
writing a number of User Properties are predefined with specific meanings.
These User Property Names begin with 'user.' and are listed below.  For
example, many reports have abstracted the concept of the user's name to
the property user.fullname.  By defining this property in your llines startup
file, it allows a report to reference your name as the source of the data
being printed without having it hard-coded in the report.
</para>
<para>
When <application>LifeLines</application> begins execution, it reads any
specified configuration files and extracts Properties from the files read.
It is possible for multiple configuration files to be read.  Properties
defined in these files will be stored in the global property table.  If
multiple definitions of the same property are seen, the latest definition
overrides prior definitions.  Configuration files are read as follows:
</para>

<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='none'>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<colspec colwidth='0.5in'></colspec>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>Note:</entry>
<entry>
If a configuration file defines LLCONFIGFILE, it is not entered in the global
table, but the value of this parameter is read as a configuration file after
completion of reading the current file.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Note:</entry>
<entry>
In the following, the name of a user configuration file is listed as
.linesrc.  On windows versions of lifelines this name is lines.cfg.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry>
If a configuration file name is passed to the program with the -C option,
or if LLCONFIGFILE is defined as an environment variable use the value
supplied as the name of the configuration file.  Do not read configuration
information from the files listed in 2a, 2b, 2c, or 2d.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2a</entry>
<entry>
If the file /etc/lifelines.conf exists, read it.  '/etc' is a placeholder for
the standard location for system configuration files as defined when 
lifelines was built.  It is often /etc or /usr/local/etc.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2b.</entry>
<entry>
If the file $HOME/.linesrc exists, load parameters from it.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2c.</entry>
<entry>
If the file .linesrc exists in the current directory read parameters from it.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>2d</entry>
<entry>
If LLCONFIGFILE is defined in the command line or database table and its 
value is the name of a file, load parameters from that file.
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para>
When <application>LifeLines</application> searches for a property it looks for it as follows:
</para>
<glosslist>

<glossentry><glossterm>cmdline table</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
First, <application>LifeLines</application> looks in the cmdline table.  This table contains the
values that have been specified using the -I option to
<application>LifeLines</application>.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>database table</glossterm><glossdef>

<para> Next, <application>LifeLines</application> looks in the database table.  This table contains the
values which have been stored in the current database.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>global table</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Next, <application>LifeLines</application> looks in the global table.  This table contains the
values found when reading in the configuration files.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>environment table</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Finally, <application>LifeLines</application> looks in the environment table.
Only a handful of properties may be set from the environment, namely 
LLPROGRAMS, LLREPORTS, LLARCHIVES, LLDATABASES, and LLEDITOR.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

<para>
Properties are named group.subgroup.property or group.property, or even
just property.
The following keys are available at the moment: 
</para>

<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm>LLPROGRAMS</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
<envar>LLPROGRAMS</envar> is the search path for
<application>LifeLines</application> report generating and
other programs.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LLREPORTS</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
<envar>LLREPORTS</envar> is used to select a directory where
all generated reports and program outputs will be placed.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LLARCHIVES</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
<envar>LLARCHIVES</envar> is used to select a
directory where all database backup files will be stored
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LLDATABASES</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
<envar>LLDATABASES</envar> is a list of
directories that contain database directories used to locate
database directories themselves
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LLNEWDBDIR</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
<envar>LLNEWDBDIR</envar> a single directory where new databases
specified without paths will be created.
This is a convenience for users
who generally put all their databases under a single common
directory.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LLEDITOR</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Overrides the default screen editor
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

<para>
Codeset Information:
</para>
<para>
For the following parameters related to codeset, the values are a 
String denoting code set in use in data. Special handling is provided
for UTF-8, which may be entered as "UTF-8", "utf-8", or "65001". (The
official, and preferred, name is UTF-8.
</para>
<glosslist>
<glossentry><glossterm>codeset</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Is a property that report programs can read whose value is the codeset of the
current database.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>GedcomCodeset</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Specifies the default Codeset to use when processing Gedcom files.
There are actually 3 properties.
<glossterm>GedcomCodesetOut</glossterm> and <glossterm>GedcomCodesetIn</glossterm>
can be used to specify the codeset for output or input.  If either of these is
not specified 
<glossterm>GedcomCodeset</glossterm> is used. Most Gedcom files should
contain a codeset property, so this is not usually relevant when reading a Gedcom
file, unless the input Gedcom file lacks a codeset property. This is used, however,
when writing out a Gedcom file. 
NB: This is ignored if the database has no internal codeset specified.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>EditorCodeset</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Specifies the codeset to use for editing.  There are actually 3 properties.
<glossterm>EditorCodesetOut</glossterm> and <glossterm>EditorCodesetIn</glossterm>
can be used to specify the codeset for output or input.  If either of these is
not specified <glossterm>EditorCodeset</glossterm> is used. This property allows
lifelines to convert from its internal codeset to the one you use in your editor, so
this is important when your editor does not use the same codeset as your database.
NB: This is ignored if the database has no internal codeset specified.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>ReportCodeset</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Specifies the codeset to use for reports.  There are actually 3 properties.
<glossterm>ReportCodesetOut</glossterm> and <glossterm>ReportCodesetIn</glossterm>
can be used to specify the codeset for output or input.  If either of these is
not specified <glossterm>ReportCodeset</glossterm> is used. Recently created
reports may actually specify their codeset, in which case this is not used, but
for reports which do not include a specification of codeset, the
<glossterm>ReportCodesetIn</glossterm> (or <glossterm>ReportCodeset</glossterm>)
specifies how the report will be understood. In any case, the output of a 
report program will be written in the codeset given by
<glossterm>ReportCodesetOut</glossterm> (or <glossterm>ReportCodeset</glossterm>).
NB: This is ignored if the database has no internal codeset specified.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>GuiCodeset</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Specifies the codeset to use for interaction with the graphical user interface.
There are actually 3 properties.
<glossterm>GuiCodesetOut</glossterm> and <glossterm>GuiCodesetIn</glossterm>
can be used to specify the codeset for output or input.  If either of these is
not specified <glossterm>GuiCodeset</glossterm> is used. 
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LongDisplayDate</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Six comma separated numbers. Specifing the format for
days, months, years, date format, era format, and complex format.
If string does not contain 6 comma separated numbers all formats are
set to 0, except date format is set to 14.
These formats are used by <application>LifeLines</application> to display dates in long format.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LongDisplayDatePic</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
a custom ymd date picture.  A string in which %y, %m and %d will be
converted to the corresponding year, month and day.
This picture is used by <application>LifeLines</application> to display dates in long format.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>ShortDisplayDate</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Six comma separated numbers. Specifing the format for
days, months, years, date format, era format, and complex format.
If string does not contain 6 comma separated numbers all formats are
set to 0, except date format is set to 14.
These formats are used by <application>LifeLines</application> to display dates in short format.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>ShortDisplayDatePic</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
a custom ymd date picture.  A string in which %y, %m and %d will be
converted to the corresponding year, month and day.
This picture is used by <application>LifeLines</application> to display dates in short format.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>LocaleDir</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
run-time specification of locale directory
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>NewDbProps</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
if specified, properties to add to a newly created database.
The string is of the form "option1=value1\noption2=value2".
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>IllegalChar</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Apparently not used at this time.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm> DenySystemCalls</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
If set to a non-zero value will disable use of the <function>system</function>
function.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>UiLocaleCollate</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
ui collating sequence
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>UiLocaleMessages</glossterm><glossdef>
<para>
ui messages locale
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>RptLocaleCollate</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Report Collating Sequence
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>RptLocaleMessages</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Report Messages Locale
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>ShortOmitString</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
If defined this string replaces characters at the end of an event being
printed.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>DisplayKeyTags</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
If set to 1 an i or f is prepended to individual and family keys when shown
on-screen.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>AnnotatePointers</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
If set to 1 a descriptive comment is added to pointers when editing family or
individual records to help identify who is being refered to.  These tags
are removed when the edit is finished and not stored in the database.
</para>

</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>TTPATH</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
list of directories to search for translation table files (*.tt)
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>TTPATH.debug</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
if defined, <application>LifeLines</application> outputs debug information
related to translation table processing.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>InputPath</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
path to look for in when reading in gedcom files
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>INDIREC</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The default template to use whenever creating a new individual.
If not specified, the concatenation of the following is used:
<programlisting>
"0 INDI\n1 NAME Fname/Surname\n1 SEX MF\n"
"1 BIRT\n  2 DATE\n  2 PLAC\n"
"1 DEAT\n  2 DATE\n  2 PLAC\n1 SOUR\n"
</programlisting>
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>FAMRECBODY</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The default template to use whenever creating a new family.
If not specified, the following is used:
<programlisting>
"1 MARR\n  2 DATE\n  2 PLAC\n  2 SOUR\n"
</programlisting>
Note: Unlike the others, this should not
include the 0 level FAM tag.)
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>SOURREC</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The default template to use whenever creating a new source.
If not specified, the following is used in english:
<programlisting>
"0 SOUR\n1 REFN\n1 TITL Title\n1 AUTH Author"
</programlisting>
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>EVENREC</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The default template to use whenever creating a new event.
If not specified, the following is used in english:
<programlisting>
"0 EVEN\n1 REFN\n1 DATE\n1 PLAC\n1 INDI\n  2 NAME\n  2 ROLE\n1 SOUR"
</programlisting>
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>OTHR</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The default template to use whenever creating a new other record.
If not specified, the following is used in english:
<programlisting>
"0 XXXX\n1 REFN"
</programlisting>
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>HDR_SUBM</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
string to use when writing gedcom files for the SUBM.
Default is 
<programlisting>
"1 SUBM".
</programlisting>
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>HDR_GEDC</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
String containing the GEDC block for the header record when exporting GEDCOM.
The default is 
<programlisting>
"1 GEDC\n2 VERS 5.5\n2 FORM LINEAGE-LINKED".
</programlisting>
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>HDR_CHAR</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Normally lifelines will populate the CHAR block in the header record
automatically when exporting GEDCOM, with the actual character encoding
being used in the export; this can be found in the settings displayed
in the u(ser) c(harset settings) page. However, if desired, the HDR_CHAR
variable may be used to overwrite the entire CHAR line.
String containing the CHAR block for the header record when exporting GEDCOM.
An example HDR_CHAR value would be "1 CHAR ASCII".
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>ReportLog</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
name of file to print report program errors to, if not specified
use stdout curses window.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>CrashLog_llexec</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
file to write crash log into for llexec.  If not set, log is written to
the file <filename>CrashLog_llexec.log</filename>.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>CrashLog_llines</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
file to write crash log into for llines. If not set, log is written to
the file <filename>CrashLog_llines.log</filename>.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
<glossentry><glossterm>LLTTEXPORT</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
directory to write translation tables to.  Default is the current
directory.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>ImportLog</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
where to log errors found while importing a gedcom file.
default is errs.log.
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>gettext.path</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
for windows, if specified path to (re)load gettext dll
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>iconv.path</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
for Windows, path to link dynamically to gettext and iconv
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>user.fullname</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The full name of the current user. If not found as a property it is fetched 
from the system when possible. 
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>user.email</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The email address of the current user. If not found as a property it is 
fetched from the system when possible. 
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>user.address</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
Postal address of the current user. 
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>user.phone</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
The phone number of the current user. 
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>

<glossentry><glossterm>user.url</glossterm><glossdef>

<para>
URL to the users home page. 
</para>
</glossdef></glossentry>
</glosslist>

</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>
Other Executables
</title>
<sect2>
<title>
dbverify
</title>
<para>
dbverify is a utility to check an existing database and report on various
inconsistencies.  It can also repair a number of issues found.
</para>
<para>
dbverify supports the following options:
</para>

<informaltable pgwide='0' frame='none'>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<colspec colwidth='0.5in'></colspec>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>-a</entry>
<entry>Perform all checks (does not include fixes)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-D </entry>
<entry>Fix bad delete entries</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-e </entry>
<entry>Check events</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-f </entry>
<entry>Check families</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-F </entry>
<entry>Alter any bad family lineage pointers (to _badptr)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry> -g </entry>
<entry>Check for ghosts (names/refns)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-G </entry>
<entry>Check for & fix ghosts (names/refns)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-h </entry>
<entry>Display help text (this text)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-i </entry>
<entry>Check individuals</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-l </entry>
<entry>Check database structure</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-m </entry>
<entry>Check for records missing data entries</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-M </entry>
<entry>Fix records missing data entries</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-n </entry>
<entry>Noisy (echo every record processed)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-s </entry>
<entry>Check sours</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>-x </entry>
<entry>Check others</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>

</informaltable>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
btedit
</title>
<para>
This program edits raw binary btree blocks in a 
<application>LifeLines</application> lifelines database file.
Some information about its usage is provided by running:
<programlisting>
btedit -h
</programlisting>
Do NOT use this unless
you know what you are doing and you have backed up
your database.
</para>
<para>
The 
<application>LifeLines</application> database has proven rather robust over
the years.  However, it is important to make frequent backups of any
database.  If you experience database corruption, make sure you save a copy
of the database before trying any recovery process.  Only work on a copy of
the data so that the data is not further damaged.
</para>
<para>
Try exporting the database to a gedcom file from within 
<command>llines</command>.  Compare the saved file with previously saved
versions.  Editing the gedcom file to correct
issues is often easier than using btedit.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>
llexec
</title>
<para>
llexec envokes the LifeLines report execution program without a GUI
for non-interactive processing of report programs.  The supported options are
the same as for <command>llines</command>.  
</para>
<para>
An example usage, which will open the database 'myfamily' and run the report
eol.ll is:
<programlisting>
llexec myfamily -x eol 
</programlisting>
Programs that require input, will prompt for that data and read from standard
input. If a program required the input of a 0 or 1 to control the output,
the following is one way to allow use of llexec in a script:
<programlisting>
echo "1" | llexec myfamily -x myprog 
</programlisting>
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
</book>
